<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quakerism is paganism, by W.L.'s confession; in a book directed to Mr. N.L. citizen of London: or, Twelve of the Quakers opinions, called by W.L. The twelve pagan principles, or opinions; for which the Quakers are opposed to Christians examined and presented to William Penn. By W. R. a lover of Christianity.</title>
            <author>Russel, William, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831209</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2040:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Quakerism is paganism, by W.L.'s confession; in a book directed to Mr. N.L. citizen of London: or, Twelve of the Quakers opinions, called by W.L. The twelve pagan principles, or opinions; for which the Quakers are opposed to Christians examined and presented to William Penn. By W. R. a lover of Christianity.</title>
                  <author>Russel, William, d. 1702.</author>
                  <author>Roberts, Daniel, 1658-1727. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, 17-96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Francis Smith, at the Elephant and Castle in Cornhil near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. R. = William Russel.</note>
                  <note>"Quakerism is popery revived: or, Some of their old opinions put into a new dress, and asserted by the Quakers to be new discoveries of the light within them" has caption title on p. 91.</note>
                  <note>Page 96 consists of "a letter from the baptized-congregation in Reading, concerning William Luddington", signed: Daniel Roberts.</note>
                  <note>Includes appendix.</note>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Loddington, William, 1626?-1711. --  Twelve pagan principles, or opinions, for which Thomas Hicks hath published the Quaker to be no Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Quakeriſm is Paganiſm, BY <hi>W. L</hi>'s Confeſſion;</p>
            <p>In a BOOK Directed to Mr. <hi>N. L.</hi> Citizen of <hi>London: OR,</hi> Twelve of the Quakers Opinions, called by <hi>W. L. The Twelve Pagan Principles,</hi> or Opinions; for which the Quakers are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Chriſtians;</p>
            <p>Examined and Preſented to <hi>WILLIAM PENN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. R.</hi> a Lover of CHRISTIANITY.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Is this thy kindneſs to thy Friend? deſiring to be a Teacher of the Law, underſtanding neither what</hi> thou <hi>ſayeſt, nor whereof</hi> thou <hi>affirmeſt,</hi> 
               <bibl>2 Sam. 16. 17. 1 Tim. 1. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Tuum Teſtimonium, quod in aliena releve eſt; id, in tua, quoniam contra te eſt, graviſſimum eſſe debet. <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero Orat. Pro. L. Q. p.</hi> 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Thy Teſtimony, which is but light and frivolous in ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers Cauſe, yet is weighty in thine own, when it's againſt thy ſelf.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil</hi> near the Royal Exchange. 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35672:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35672:2"/>
            <head>QUAKERISM is PAGANISM, By <hi>W. L's</hi> Confeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> OR, <hi>Twelve of the</hi> Quakers <hi>Opinions;</hi> Examined and preſented TO <hi>WILLIAM PENN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I deſign not to traduce the Perſon of any Man, nor wrong him in his Sentiments about Religion; much leſs your ſelf in this Undertaking; having a high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe natural and acquired Parts, which manifeſt themſelves more conſpicuouſly in you, than in many others of your Friends: But theſe being alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but Meteors adding Blaze, little of true Brightneſs, They have an umbrage of Grandeur, not a Spark of Saving Grace, or Dram of Heavenly Glory. The <hi>Enamel</hi> of thoſe attainments are apt to fully and expire; and the Poſſeſſor in endeavouring to ſtand accerſeth his fall. It is an Intereſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Conformity to his Will, as it is Revealed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35672:3"/>
Scriptures, and a Conſtant Perſeverance therein; that would make you truly happy to Eternity.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Sir,</hi> I would imploy my Pen at this time, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to intreat you, to examine what Ground you ſtand on; whether you have good Principles to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port you? for I fear you ſtand in a ſlippery place; and that great will be your fall, without a timely Prevention.</p>
            <p>It is my deſign to be Inſtrumental (among others) to perſwade you to <hi>own the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> whom to me you ſeem to deny: And to ſubmit your ſelf to his Laws, recorded in Holy Scripture; which you now Slight and Trample upon. That thoſe Parts which God hath been pleaſed to Honour you withal, might be imployed to his Glory and the Salvation of your Soul, which are Matters moſt ſublime and weighty.</p>
            <p>It is certain Chriſt will come in flaming Fire to take Vengeance on thoſe that obey not the Goſpel as it was at firſt delivered to the Saints; and much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Vengeance may they expect, who Deny him and Oppoſe themſelves againſt it: For God will Judg Men by the Goſpel as a Rule, and by the Man Chriſt Jeſus as their Judg, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16. For he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Day in the which he will Judg the World in Righteouſneſs, by that <hi>Man</hi> whom he hath Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and whom you Reject, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 31. I pray God you have not cauſe one day to remember that you have been told ſo, but refuſed to be Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> If upon ſecond thoughts you find you have gone too far, and have eſpouſed a Cauſe not to be Juſtified by the Principles of right Reaſon and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, count it not a diſhonour to Retract. It<hi>'s</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35672:3"/>
no wrong to you or any man (but a kindneſs) to be delivered from an <hi>Error,</hi> it will be your advantage and honour to imbrace Truth, when-ever you are <hi>convinced and inlightened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Sir,</hi> If you are confidently perſwaded of the Truth of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles, as you profeſs; pray tell the World the Reaſon why you are ſo <hi>ſhy in diſcovering, ſo unwilling to confeſs, them,</hi> (for Truth ſeeks no Corners to hide her ſelf) ſtand forth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare you own thoſe Doctrines; or let us know you are of another Mind, by rejecting the Men and their Books in which thoſe Opinions (as charged upon you) are Aſſerted: Think not to hide yourſelves under <hi>a Mask of Evaſive pretences,</hi> and <hi>Clouds of Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences and Railery;</hi> for that is <hi>ſeen through,</hi> and will be daily more and more by thoſe that are judicious, to your great Reproach, notwithſtanding all your <hi>Stratagems</hi> to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Among which I do find, That as you have taken <hi>New-ways,</hi> ſo there are <hi>New-Advocates</hi> riſen up to plead your Cauſe; and propagate your Principles; one of which I have now taken upon me to Examine: I do promiſe you to do him Juſtice, though he hath been Unjuſt to himſelf and others; and do preſent my Sentiments of him to be Conſidered by you, for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe I underſtand he is an Intimate <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Aſſociate</hi> of <hi>yours,</hi> and it may be you are more <hi>privy</hi> to what he hath done in this Matter than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man, and ſo more capable to Judg of what I ſhall ſay.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe he hath <hi>Eſpouſed</hi> your <hi>Quarrel,</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> obligeth you to aſſiſt him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe he hath <hi>oppoſed your Sentiments</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35672:4"/>
Mr. <hi>HICKS:</hi> You call him a <hi>Lyar,</hi> a <hi>Forger,</hi> and what not? <hi>W. L.</hi> layes <hi>no ſuch thing to his Charge,</hi> but calls him <hi>his Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe I would have you return an Anſwer in Print, that we may know whether your mind be yet altered or not, touching Mr. <hi>HICKS,</hi> and theſe <hi>Twelve Pagan Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe, if you ſhall inſiſt upon the Confutation of Mr. <hi>HICKS,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of theſe <hi>Particulars,</hi> that you would be pleaſed, not barely to <hi>call</hi> him a <hi>Lyar, Forger, Slanderer,</hi> &amp;c. but ſhew wherein he hath <hi>belyed</hi> you in any of them.</p>
            <p>I will firſt ſpeak to the <hi>Title of</hi> William Ludding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton<hi>'s Book,</hi> which is <hi>The Twelve Pagan Principles:</hi> And my Opinion is, he hath <hi>rightly named</hi> them, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I think he may have the honour of the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and if <hi>W. L.</hi> ſay true, then a <hi>Quaker is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and no true Chriſtian;</hi> for he <hi>Confeſſes</hi> they hold <hi>thoſe Opinions</hi> he calls by that <hi>Name,</hi> and as <hi>He</hi> and <hi>I</hi> are agreed herein, ſo is <hi>T. H.</hi> alſo, by <hi>his own Confeſſion:</hi> for he ſaith, it is for <hi>thoſe Opinions,</hi> he hath <hi>Publiſhed the Quaker</hi> to be <hi>no Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith, he hath <hi>ſeriouſly conſidered them:</hi> but he gives me ground to think otherwiſe, in paſſing-over ſome things <hi>ſlightly, extenuating</hi> others, and <hi>avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſimply</hi> what he could not <hi>ſubtilly evade,</hi> or ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>confute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas he ſaith, <hi>Preſented to Mr.</hi> N. L. <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of</hi> London<hi>:</hi> I do make bold to tell him, That he is much diſpleaſed with that <hi>cauſeleſs</hi> and <hi>impertinent</hi> Preſent: and were not he known to be a <hi>worthy Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> a Man of <hi>Integrity,</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> in the Principles of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> This had been <hi>Indication,</hi> ſufficient to bring him into ſome Suſpicion with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35672:4"/>
as if he were <hi>tottering</hi> in the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity: W. L.</hi> being known to be a Man faſt of <hi>Whimſies,</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſtical Notions,</hi> about the moſt <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>weighty</hi> Points of the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> of which this Book is no ſmall Teſtimony: But by this we may ſee what ways are invented to impoſe upon the World when they are in a ſtrait.</p>
            <p>Touching theſe <hi>Pagan Principles</hi> as <hi>W. L.</hi> calls them, I am more confirmed in my Opinion, that theſe are <hi>the very Principles of the Quakers</hi> from what he hath written: being perſwaded, That if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue writing for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> as he hath begun, not only in this Book, but alſo in that Impertinent <hi>Letter</hi> of his to Mr. <hi>Ives;</hi> he will do the like kindneſs for the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> as that Man did for his Enemy, of whom it's Storied, <hi>That he thruſt his Sword into his Body with an intent to kill him, but inſtead thereof, let out an Impoſthume which was a means of his preſervation:</hi> And my Reaſons for it are theſe.</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe he doth not deny <hi>any one</hi> of thoſe Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es laid upon them by Mr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> but under each Head, he acts the part of an <hi>Advocate;</hi> I wiſh he had better <hi>Clients,</hi> and a better <hi>Cauſe.</hi> The Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (he ſaith) are <hi>Pagan,</hi> and the Men are <hi>no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Neither indeed do they impoſe upon us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them ſo, nor have they that Appollation given them; bur inſtead thereof, they <hi>call</hi> themſelves, and are <hi>called</hi> by others, <hi>Quakers.</hi> He endeavours to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> them, from what they cannot <hi>Excuſe themſelves,</hi> without a manifeſt <hi>injury</hi> to their <hi>own Opinions:</hi> And where this will not do, he labours to <hi>Extenuate</hi> the Fault by <hi>ſubſtracting from,</hi> and adding <hi>to</hi> the <hi>Quakers Sayings;</hi> and then tells us, it is but a <hi>little word;</hi> as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35672:5"/>
putting in <hi>(OF)</hi> and taking away <hi>(IRRELIGIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.)</hi> But ſure leſs than either of theſe may <hi>totally</hi> deſtroy the ſence; as will appear by theſe following inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is, That a Compoſitor (that was a Papiſt) being imployed at the King's Printing-Houſe in the Days of King <hi>James,</hi> took out of the <hi>7th</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Particle <hi>(NOT)</hi> and then it was thus read, <hi>Thou ſhalt Commit Adultery,</hi> and that was leſs than the word <hi>(Irreligious:)</hi> and it was then eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſo great a crime,</hi> that (it's ſaid) the <hi>Printer</hi> was <hi>fined</hi> a 1000 Pounds.</p>
            <p>In the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 51. where it's ſaid, <hi>We ſhall not all ſleep, but we ſhall all be Changed;</hi> leave out but <hi>(C)</hi> and then it muſt be read, <hi>we ſhall all be Hanged:</hi> and yet this is leſs than <hi>(OF.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such liberty as this being allowed, I will make my Antagoniſt ſpeak what I liſt; but this is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Author; I hope I may be allowed the liberty of thinking that the man is in a ſtrait.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe where <hi>he cannot deny</hi> but <hi>thoſe words were ſpoken by the Quakers,</hi> which <hi>T. H.</hi> charges upon them; and that they do alſo <hi>bear the ſame ſence</hi> which he puts upon them: there he endeavours to perſwade us that they may alſo <hi>bear another ſence;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>It's a ſign of hatred to catch at the worſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from thence I perceive (if <hi>W. L.</hi> ſay true) That the Quakers Words are delivered as <hi>Ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,</hi> as the <hi>Heathen gods</hi> uſed to deliver their <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;</hi> that ſo the <hi>falſity</hi> thereof may be the <hi>leſs capable</hi> of <hi>detection.</hi> A Man of great credit among the Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, named <hi>Oenomaus,</hi> who for that he had been much <hi>delighted</hi> with <hi>Oracles,</hi> and more <hi>deceived;</hi> wrote a Book, in the end, of their <hi>Falſhoods</hi> and <hi>Lyes;</hi> and yet ſheweth, That in many things wherein they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35672:5"/>
               <hi>deceived,</hi> it was <hi>not eaſy</hi> to convince them of <hi>open Falſhood;</hi> for that they would involve their anſwer (on purpoſe) with ſuch <hi>Obſcurities, Generalities, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocations, and Doubtfulneſs,</hi> that they would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways leave themſelves a <hi>Corner</hi> wherein to ſave their <hi>Credits,</hi> when the event ſhould prove <hi>falſe.</hi> As for Example, <hi>When Craeſus that famous and rich Monarch of</hi> Lydia, <hi>conſulted with the Oracle of</hi> Apollo, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould make War againſt the</hi> Perſians, <hi>and thereby obtain their Empire or no?</hi> Apollo <hi>deſirous of Bloodſhed (as the wicked ſpirits are) gave his Oracle in theſe words, for deceiving of</hi> Craeſus. If <hi>Craeſus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear, ſhall paſs over <hi>Halys, (this was a River that lay between him and</hi> Perſia) he ſhall bring to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a great Rich Kingdom. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which words,</hi> Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <hi>paſſed over his Army, in hopes to get</hi> Perſia; <hi>but ſoon after he loſt</hi> Lydia, <hi>by an evil underſtanding of this doubtful Prophecy.</hi> Euſebius, <hi>Lib.</hi> de Praep. Evan. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Surely, all ſuch dark unintelligible language (in my underſtanding) ought to be exploded by all the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and all <hi>true Chriſtians;</hi> for it hath no better tendency, than to <hi>deceive</hi> and <hi>beguile</hi> ignorant and unſtable Souls. This was not the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Holy Apoſtles, of our dear Redeemer the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who delivered their Doctrines in the moſt <hi>plain and intelligible words</hi> that might be, for the inſtruction and information of their Auditors; eſpecially about the great and moſt important Truths of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> as the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, 1 Theſſ. 2. 3, 4. <hi>For our exhortation was not of Deceit, nor of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, nor in Guile; but as we were allowed of God to be put in Truſt with the Goſpel, ſo we ſpeak: for if the Trumpet give an uncertain ſound, who ſhall prepare himſelf to the Battle? So likewiſe</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35672:6"/>
               <hi>you, except ye utter by the Tongue words eaſy to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, how ſhall it be known what is ſpoken, for ye ſhall ſpeak into the Air,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 8, 9. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contrary is found in the Quakers, as appears, not only <hi>by this Man's Confeſſion,</hi> but alſo by <hi>their Writings and Expreſſions,</hi> as is <hi>obvious to all</hi> that have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them. Surely they are not guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord, their Practice being ſo contrary to the <hi>firſt Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and ſo agreeable to the Method uſed by the <hi>Falſe gods</hi> among the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> whoſe Words and Writings are like their <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> i. e. full of <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Ambiguity.</hi> And if <hi>W. L.</hi> thinks this to be the way to make Men in Love with Quakeriſm, it muſt be ſuch <hi>that are men of corrupt Minds, Reprobate concerning the Faith:</hi> As for me, I will ſay of all ſuch vile and deceitful Practices, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> touching that wicked Act of theirs. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 6. <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret, unto their Aſſembly, mine honour be not thou united.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe in theſe 12. <hi>Pagan Principles,</hi> he hath cleered <hi>T. H.</hi> of thoſe <hi>Black Charges</hi> the Quakers have laid upon him; in calling him <hi>Lyar, Forger, Slanderer,</hi> &amp;c. For if theſe words were <hi>ſpoken</hi> by the Quakers, or <hi>written</hi> in their <hi>Books,</hi> then he cannot be a <hi>Lyar, Forger,</hi> &amp;c. And that they are ſo, take <hi>W. L.'s Confeſſion</hi> under each Head, (as they ſtand in his Book) in the method following.</p>
            <div n="1" type="principle">
               <head>1. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt Opinion Charged upon the Quakers is, <hi>That the Light in every man, or the Light with which every Man is enlightned, is God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35672:6"/>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>How ſmall a Word would ſtop this Breach? put in but</hi> (OF) <hi>and all's well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> By the ſame Rule, where the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that doth good is of God;</hi> John 3. Epiſtle <hi>v.</hi> 11. Take out but (OF) and then it is thus; <hi>He that doth good is God;</hi> which as it refers to men, as by the ſcope of the place is evident; it is not only an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth,</hi> but <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> Neither will that relieve him to bring in <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaying, <hi>That every ſuch Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination is not very God,</hi> for if it were, then <hi>W. P.</hi> muſt believe there were as <hi>many Gods</hi> as there are <hi>Men in the World;</hi> becauſe he faith that every man hath that Illumination: For <hi>W. P.</hi> in his Reaſon againſt Rayling, <hi>Page</hi> 56. ſaith, Geo. Whitehead <hi>owns it in its own being to be no other than God himſelf; where he approves of that ſaying, and adds this to it himſelf; We aſſert the true Light with which every man is enlightned, to be in it ſelf the Chriſt of God, and the Saviour of the World.</hi> Now if <hi>W. P.</hi> will contradict himſelf, who can help that? it's not <hi>T. H.</hi> his fault, but his own. Reader, here <hi>he confeſſes the charge,</hi> ſo that Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> is <hi>no Forger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="principle">
               <head>2. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIS Second Charge is, <hi>That the Soul is a Part of God, and of God's Being, without beginning and Infinite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>What hurt is there in this? if they do ſay ſo: I never heard the</hi> Heathen <hi>were of this Opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſee no cauſe to be offended, much leſs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them</hi> Heathen, <hi>if the</hi> Quakers <hi>do count it a part of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Surely this Man is little Read in Heathen Authors, that he can ſay he never heard the Heathen
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35672:7"/>
were of this Opinion <hi>that the Soul is a Part of God &amp;c.</hi> Let him but read <hi>Seneca</hi> (I preſume he hath learning enough to do it becauſe he is a Schoolmaſter) and he will find him to be of this very Opinion; Theſe are his Words, <hi>Quid aliud voces animum, quam Deum in Corpore humano hoſpitantem:</hi> What can we call the Soul (ſaith he) but God abiding in an humane Body? And of the Reaſon wherewith the Soul of Man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed he affirms, that it is <hi>Part of the Divine Spirit in Man's Body:</hi> For theſe are his Words, <hi>Ratio nihil aliud eſt, quam in corpus humanum pars Divini Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> &amp;c. Seneca <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 67. So that if I would trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf and you, I could ſhew you that herein there is a great union between a <hi>Quaker</hi> and a <hi>Pagan</hi> in their Opinion about the Soul of Man; the which may be moſt elegantly detected in the Words of a Learned Author of our times, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>It is a little Deity gueſting in a body of Fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Reader thou mayeſt ſee that <hi>T. H.</hi> is no <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and alſo that <hi>W. L.</hi> (though ignorantly) hath <hi>rightly</hi> called this <hi>A Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The great Heat of diſputes of that nature, has cauſed a ſcoffing Poet to Rhyme thus of</hi> OUR <hi>Diſputes;</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Theſe Diſputants like Rams and Bulls,</l>
                  <l>Do fight with Arms that ſpring from Skulls;</l>
                  <l>And when they argue the greateſt Part,</l>
                  <l>O'th Conteſt falls on Terms of Art.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Who would but think theſe Verſes had been made upon the late Diſputes <hi>between us and the Quakers</hi> as <hi>W. L.</hi> words it? and yet I find that <hi>Hudibras</hi> is the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35672:7"/>
Poet, and the Title of the Book tells me<hi>: it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the time of the late War, and Licenſed</hi> November 11. 1662. <hi>Hudibras</hi> Part 1. page 267. <hi>Canto</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>But I perceive he can allow himſelf a liberty to ſay any thing, yea rather than <hi>T. H.</hi> ſhall go free, he will jeer his Friend <hi>W. P.</hi> alſo; for if the Author of the <hi>Quakers Quibbles</hi> be not much miſtaken, the great fault (which made that Diſpute ſo fruitleſs) lay in <hi>W. P.</hi> and his Friends; for in <hi>page</hi> 10. he asks <hi>W. P.</hi> this queſtion: <q>When thou cameſt to the Reaſoning and Diſputative part, how many ſhuffles and put-offs? How many pittiful Evaſions and poor ſhifts didſt thou make? how many delays? how much loſs of time? I was not only aſhamed to ſee it, but admired thy ſelf and Friends did not bluſh at it, to ſee you make yourſelves and party ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous in the Eyes of others: What Rayling inſtead of Reaſoning! What Clamour! What Noiſe! What Tautologies! What Diſorder! What Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Confuſion! No Argument to me more fully proved you to be no Chriſtians, than your Unchriſtian carriage in that Meeting.</q> And he that ſpeaks this is an Indifferent Perſon, neither Quaker nor Baptiſt.</p>
               <p>As for the abuſe he hath done to the Poet in repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the two firſt lines otherwiſe than they are in <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibras,</hi> I queſtion not but <hi>Hudibras</hi> knows how to right himſelf better than I can direct him; in the mean time I would adviſe <hi>W. L.</hi> to take that good advice <hi>noſec tripſum,</hi> to ſtudy the knowledg of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more, and then he will not be at ſo much leiſure to pry into the lives, and eſpouſe the Quarrel of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men: had he been ſo imployed when he wrote this Book, he had ſaved me this pains; for I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35672:8"/>
him that I don't uſe to imploy my Time after this ſort; nor would I have done it now, only I hope God may have ſome Honour by detecting his folly, and it may be I may be made Inſtrumental to bring him to a ſight of it.</p>
               <p>I had thought to have paſſed over this Head, but the man makes ſuch a ſtir about an impertinent Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that I am minded to ſay ſomething to it, leſt my ſilence ſhould prove his prejudice.</p>
               <p>Queſt. But, <hi>Why</hi> (ſaith <hi>W. L.) may not we aſwel ſay, God hath given us a Part of himſelf; as a Part or Meaſure of his ſpirit which hath no beginning nor end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, as it is in the Queſtion, and relates to the Soul of Man; I will tell you why we may not ſo ſpeak, becauſe there is a great Diſparity betwixt the Soul of Man, and the Spirit of God: As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Soul of Man is a Creature made by God. Iſaiah 57. 16. <hi>For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth, for the Spirit ſhould fail before me, and the Souls which I have made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But the Holy Spirit is <hi>increated</hi> and of the ſame <hi>Eſſence</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> as the Quaker himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, and from thence takes occaſion to confound the Perſonal Exiſtence of all the Three.</p>
               <p>Now, though I may ſay God hath given us a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Spirit, becauſe we are made to partake of the <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> thereof; yet I may not affirm that therefore the <hi>Soul</hi> in which they do reſide, <hi>is a part of God and of God's Being, without Beginning and Infinite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſays W. L. <hi>That Man hath an Immortal Soul we all grant;</hi> and yet before he is got ten lines for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he ſaith, <hi>if the Soul be a Created part of Man coming by Generation, then</hi> (as I have heard it argued)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35672:8"/>
                  <hi>it muſt be Mortal:</hi> and a little after. <hi>This is a great Miſtery, and we muſt wait till another Seal of the Book of Life be opened, before we ſhall know what the Breath of Life was which God Breathed into</hi> Adam, Gen. 2. He ſaith, <hi>Philoſophers and Divines have made a great Buſtle about the Soul, but to define what it is, will be as hard a Task, as it was to one</hi> Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, <hi>to tell what God was; but ſtill we are as wiſe as before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Truly I don't expect to be made wiſer by this diſcourſe of thine about the Soul; but give me leave to ask thee a few queſtions about it, notwithſtanding thy conſidence in ſaying <hi>It's ſtrange we ſhould differ about we know not what.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Doſt thou believe the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man was <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Doſt thou not believe God to be <hi>Increated,</hi> to ſubſiſt of, and from himſelf, and from no other?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Doſt thou believe it poſſible for the Bleſſed <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi> of all things to become a <hi>Creature;</hi> or for a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to be made <hi>God</hi> Bleſſed for evermore, and to be <hi>without beginning and infinite?</hi> He that can believe this, may eaſily believe Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>I would have <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>W. L.</hi> conſult together once more, and ſee if they can invent ſome Anſwer that may Reconcile theſe 2 Propoſitions:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man was <hi>Created.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Soul</hi> is God himſelf, <hi>without beginning and infinite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is aſſerted by God himſelf, Eſay 57. 16. <hi>The Souls which I have made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The latter is aſſerted by themſelves, for they ſay <hi>the Soul is a part of God's Being,</hi> &amp;c. and in this caſe that known Maxim will ſtand good, <hi>Quidquid eſt in</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35672:9"/>
                  <hi>Deo, eſt Deus:</hi> Whatſoever <hi>is in God, is God.</hi> Now if they cannot Reconcile them, if I come to be put to my choyce whether I will Believe <hi>God's Word</hi> or <hi>Their's,</hi> I ſhall not only believe what God hath ſpoken, but alſo that <hi>his Word will certainly ſtand againſt them for Evil.</hi> Jer. 44. ult. <hi>For they have rejected the Word of the Lord, and what Wiſdom is in them?</hi> Now I hope <hi>W. L.</hi> may ſee, notwithſtanding all that he hath ſaid, That though the Soul of Man be made Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and can never Die, yet it had not always a Being, it is not without beginning; there being a time when it was not, and that it is not <hi>infinite and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I wonder <hi>W. L.</hi> ſhould ſay <hi>that it is ſo hard to know what the Soul is;</hi> he forgets ſure that the Quakers have a light in them that (they ſay) <hi>can teach them all things:</hi> if they cannot know what it is, now the Scripture hath ſo plainly told them that Man hath a Soul, ſurely they would have been hard put to it to have told us <hi>that,</hi> and all other things <hi>Recorded in Scripture</hi> concerning <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus, the Holy Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Souls of Men;</hi> if they had not been written there. Notwithſtanding they have often told us, That they could have known all thoſe things contained in the Bible if they had never been written: But I am glad we are not forced to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to them for the knowledg thereof; for if we were, I have ground to conclude we muſt go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; for I have often asked, What ſome of thoſe things were that our Saviour did when he was upon the Earth that are not written? But they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell me one of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="principle">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35672:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Pagan Principle the</hi> 3d.</head>
               <p>THe Third Opinion charged on the <hi>Quakers</hi> is, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt is not a diſtinct Perſon without us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>Theſe Expreſſions being not in Scripture are not owned by them, and why we ſhould impoſe them I know not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reader, here is a plain confeſſion that the Quakers do not own Jeſus Chriſt to be a Diſtinct Perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, therefore <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger.</p>
               <p>But I will examine his Reaſon why they do not own it; It is (ſaith he) <hi>Becauſe it is not expreſſed in the Scripture:</hi> Now in caſe that ſuppoſition were true, that cannot be the Reaſon why the Quakers do deny it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For firſt, <hi>They deny the Scriptures to be a Rule of Faith and Practice unto Chriſtians,</hi> and therefore though they may ſometimes make uſe of them againſt thoſe that own them <hi>Argumentum ad hominem,</hi> as I may make uſe of the ſaying of a Heathen Poet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Heathen; yet it's ſhameful for a Quaker hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exploded them in print from being a Rule of Faith, to bring this as a Reaſon why they do not own it, <hi>becauſe</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>it is not written in Scripture;</hi> and as <hi>W. P.</hi> doth, in calling this Doctrine of <hi>T. H. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural:</hi> ſeeing all the real ground a Quaker can have to own any Doctrine is, <hi>Becauſe he is Taught it by the Light within:</hi> and the pretence of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof to himſelf is but vain; for that's the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether the Quakers themſelves do believe Chriſt to be a Diſtinct Perſon without them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35672:10"/>
2. But Secondly, Theſe Expreſſions of <hi>T. H.</hi> are no more in effect than if I ſhould ſay in other words, <hi>That Chriſt is a Man without us:</hi> and is he not called in Scripture <hi>the MAN Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5. For ſurely to ſay he is a MAN, is to ſuppoſe him both to be <hi>diſtinct,</hi> and a <hi>Perſon</hi> without us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But Chriſt is ſaid to be in his People, and to dwell in them</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I grant it, but the Scripture ſaith <hi>it is by the Spirit,</hi> 1 John 4. 13. <hi>Hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us; becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit.</hi> Chap. 3. 24. <hi>And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us; neither is this to be underſtood of the Eſſence, but of the Gifts and Graces of the Spirit, therefore it's ſaid ſo,</hi> Epheſ. 3. 16, 17. where the Apoſtle prayes, that they might be ſtrengthened with Might, by his Spirit in the inner Man; <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your Hearts by FAITH.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But thirdly, I will prove that Chriſt is called a PERSON in Scripture. <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. 24. <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaith, <hi>I am innocent of the Blood of this</hi> JUST PERSON: If they ſay he was a wicked man that ſaid ſo, then it ſeems a wicked Man did own more concerning Chriſt than a Quaker is willing to do: But I can prove that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth that very Expreſſion, 2 Cor. 2. 10. <hi>For your ſakes forgave I it in the</hi> PERSON of CHRIST: and this doth not only prove Chriſt to be a PERSON, but alſo that he is a DISTINCT PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON <hi>without us;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> doth here tell the Church, that in that Act he did Repreſent the PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON of Chriſt, he being (in reſpect of his HU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANE NATURE) abſent, and in Heaven; and that he acted in his ſtead. But ſurely the Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35672:10"/>
the Quakers make againſt the PERSON of Chriſt <hi>is wholly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural;</hi> Never any true Miniſter or Chriſtian mentioned in Scripture did ever oppoſe this Doctrine of Chriſt's being <hi>a Diſtinct</hi> PERSON <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us,</hi> if they did, let them ſhew it us in their Next.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But Fourthly, Seeing Syllogizing (which they formerly condemned) is now grown into Faſhion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; I will give them one Argument to prove Chriſt Jeſus to be a REAL and True MAN.</p>
               <p>If all the Properties of a <hi>Humane Perſon</hi> were found in Chriſt, then he was a <hi>Real</hi> and True <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all the Properties of a <hi>Humane Perſon</hi> were found in Chriſt; Ergo, he was a <hi>Real and True Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To deny the conſequence of the Major, is to take away the very Rule of Diſtinction between the <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of different Creatures;</hi> ſo that if that be denyed, then they may call a Man a Horſe, and no body can contradict them.</p>
               <p>The Minor I prove thus: The Scripture tells us that Chriſt was <hi>made Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>made</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of DAVID according to the Fleſh; <hi>made</hi> of a <hi>Woman,</hi> did partake of the <hi>ſame</hi> Fleſh and Blood that Children do, that he was <hi>Born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, he did <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>thirſt, eat</hi> and <hi>drink, ſpeak</hi> and <hi>ſleep,</hi> was ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all our Temptations; yea, <hi>was Tempted in all points as we are,</hi> did Travel from one place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was expoſed to ſo many Sufferings, that he was called <hi>A MAN of Sorrows;</hi> and laſtly, as the greateſt Demonſtration thereof, He who had a <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul,</hi> and a <hi>True Body</hi> did lay down his Life as a Ranſom for us, being himſelf <hi>Subject to Death, even the Death of the Croſs;</hi> from all which I draw this Concluſion, <hi>Chriſt was a Real and true Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35672:11"/>
But ſaith W. L. <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh is yet ſo great a Myſtery, that I know no Catechiſms free from ſome ſeeming incongruities, attending the queſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Sure he ſhould have excepted <hi>Smith's Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the Quakers great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>George Fox;</hi> for they ſay <hi>they ſpeak and write by an Infalliable Spirit,</hi> unleſs he doth not believe they have <hi>Immediate Revelation for the Rule of their Faith and Practice,</hi> notwithſtanding they ſo confidently Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it. But perhaps we are to underſtand him thus, That though there be ſome ſeeming Incongruities in them, yet they are not Really Incongruous; if ſo, then the diſpute about that point may ſoon be ended? But to take him, as I conceive he would be underſtood, and as indeed his words do ſignifie, then it's to make this Doctrine ſo doubtful, that (in his ſence) it is loſt labour to enquire about the Truth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>viz. Whether Chriſt be Really a diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon without us, or no?</hi> and a thing not to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
               <p>To that I would give this Anſwer; It doth not follow that becauſe there may be ſome Queſtions ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the Manner, how that great Work was Accompliſhed, of God's being Manifeſt in the Fleſh, (which is the wonder of Men and Angels) that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reſolved by any Man; That therefore we ſhould diſown it (as the Quakers do,) and conclude that no man can know <hi>de facto</hi> that ſuch a thing was: For though I do not know what moved <hi>W. L.</hi> to write, nor what reward he expects for writing; yet I know he did write: <hi>W. L.</hi> cannot tell me <hi>how the Bones do grow in the Womb of her that is with Child:</hi> and yet he knows they did grow there, or elſe they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35672:11"/>
had not been. He cannot tell me <hi>how the Corn that is caſt into the Earth doth grow to be what it is at Harveſt;</hi> and yet he knows it is ſo: <hi>A Stalk, an Ear,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Argument that <hi>W. L.</hi> makes it doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>whether Chriſt be a diſtinct Perſon without us,</hi> and the Quakers deny him ſo to be; a man may make it doubtful, yea deny <hi>that ever the Heavens and Earth were made,</hi> and ſo not only be <hi>no Chriſtian,</hi> but an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt:</hi> for it's evident, when the moſt learned Men come to examine every point concerning the Creation of the Heavens and Earth, and the things therein; as, how, and what, and where, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and when things were done? it doth aſtoniſh them all, to conſider the difficulties which they find, and the depth of ſuch infinite and inſcrutable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. We may as well by <hi>William Luddington</hi>'s way of reaſoning conclude that theſe things had no beginning; nay, that they are not, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture ſaith ſo plainly, Gen. 1. 1. <hi>In the Beginning God created the Heavens and the Earth,</hi> and we ſee them with our Eyes. And by the ſame parity of Reaſon, becauſe our Saviour ſaith John 3. 8. <hi>That the Wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth;</hi> A Man may conclude that the Wind hath not its <hi>Origination</hi> and <hi>Termination:</hi> but how abſurd ſuch a concluſion would be, I leave to the Judicious to determine.</p>
               <p>I hope <hi>W. L.</hi> will acknowledg, That it is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable duty of all Men, <hi>to know God, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is;</hi> and yet there may be ſome Queſtions asked about it, that no man living can reſolve. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Quakers themſelves, <hi>though they ſay their Soul is a part of God, and the light they have in them is God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35672:12"/>
yet they would be as much puzzled, and find as hard a Task on't, as <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith <hi>one</hi> Simonides <hi>did, when he took upon him to define what God was.</hi> But muſt we therefore turn Fools and Atheiſts like him that Holy <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, Pſalm 14. 1. <hi>And ſay in our Hearts there is no God.</hi> Reader, I am greatly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended when I find men trifle (as this Man doth) about the moſt Sacred and Divine Truths of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and ſtrain their Wits, to root up Religion out of the minds of Men, for I know (through grace) that nothing can make a man ſo happy as to be truely Religious; that inriches the Soul with Divine Truths and Heavenly Graces: but theſe Men take away him, whom the Father hath anointed and filled with Grace and Truth, and appointed to reveal unto us the moſt glorious Truths of the Goſpel, and to give us Grace to inable us to obey his Will, from whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and firſt Chriſtians did receive BOTH. John. 1. 16, 17. <hi>And of his fulneſs have all we received, and Grace for Grace: For the Law was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>but</hi> GRACE <hi>and</hi> TRUTH <hi>came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It's not ſufficient for them to ſay, they do own there is a Chriſt, when they intend not the MAN Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, but a Chriſt of their own ſetting up, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as ſuch, to wit, <hi>the Light within them;</hi> For our Saviour ſaith, <hi>If ye believe not that I am HE, ye ſhall dye in your Sins,</hi> John 8. 24. The JEWS could have ſaid aſmuch for themſelves as that, and more too; for they did not deny a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> but, believed he ſhould come: yea, and be a MAN alſo, when he did come; yet they and the Quakers are both agreed, that the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus</hi> that is come in the Fleſh is not HE<hi>:</hi> and that the True Chriſt can never dye and be made a Sacrifice for Sin. That the Jews were of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35672:12"/>
this Opinion, ſee John 12. 32, 33, 34. <hi>And</hi> I, <hi>if</hi> I <hi>be lifted up from the Earth, will draw all men unto me.</hi> (This he ſaid, ſignifying what death he ſhould dye) <hi>The People anſwered him, We have heard out of the Law, That</hi> CHRIST <hi>abideth for</hi> EVER<hi>: And how ſayeſt thou the</hi> SON of MAN <hi>muſt be lift up? Who</hi> is this SON of MAN? That made them to ſay when he was upon the Croſs; <hi>If thou be the Son of God, come down from the Croſs;</hi> Matt. 27. 40. and in <hi>verſ.</hi> 42. The Chief Prieſts, Elders, and Scribes mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſaying, HE <hi>ſaved others Himſelf he cannot ſave: If he be the King of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>let him now come down from the Croſs, and we will believe him.</hi> That the Quakers do alſo deny Chriſt's Death, and ſay, That he never did Dye; I and many others have been Ear-Witneſſes, to the great grief and trouble of our Souls. But though theſe Men can ſo eaſily part with their Saviour; I hope when they or others tempt me ſo to do, I ſhall ſay, (and ſo I hope will many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that fear God) as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> did, LORD, <hi>to whom ſhall we go? thou haſt the Words of Eternal Life: And we believe, and are ſure, that thou art THAT Chriſt the Son of the Living God,</hi> John 6. 68, 69.</p>
               <p>Reader, I would not have detained thee ſo long upon this ſubject, but to let thee ſee, That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſuch inſinuations is to make void plain and moſt neceſſary Truths, that they may the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce their own corrupt Principles: For it is not only in this, but about many other the moſt Important Truths of Chriſtianity, which they endeavour to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade by raiſing Difficulties about the MODE of things, when we enquire not into the <hi>Manner how it ſhall be,</hi> but TRUTH <hi>of the Matter</hi> whether it is or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35672:13"/>
ſhall ever be? and I will give thee one inſtance, in the room of many more; which I could give upon my own knowledg if there were occaſion.</p>
               <p>I have asked many of the Quakers, Whether they did believe, that the ſame Body which doth now conſiſt of Fleſh, Blood and Bones, and is buried, ſhall be raiſed again out of the Grave, and made Spiritual and Glorious?</p>
               <p>The Anſwer they uſed to give me was, <hi>Thou art one of them Fools that</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaks of, that art inquiring about the manner how, what Body it ſhall have? &amp;c.</hi> thinking thereby to have evaded and dropt the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: But at length, when I have preſt them for a plain and full Anſwer, and deſired them to tell me <hi>not how it ſhould be raiſed,</hi> or with what a Body <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Form; But whether the ſame Body that dies ſhall Riſe again,</hi> reſpecting <hi>the Matter</hi> of which it doth Conſiſt? And they have often told me, <hi>That that Body which Dies ſhall not Riſe again.</hi> But to return from whence I have digreſſed.</p>
               <p>W. L. ſaith; <hi>Nevertheleſs we and they agree, That he is unworthy to be called a Chriſtian that denies the Divinity of Chriſt, and brings divers Scriptures to prove it:</hi> But, (ſaith he) <hi>When from other Texts more dark, we are taught to underſtand our Lord Jeſus to be that very</hi> Jehovah, <hi>Creator or Father; of whom and to whom he himſelf ſpeaks when he ſaith, My Father is greater than I. And Father I will, that whom thou haſt given me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>with many more of that kind: then I ſay, Are not our Apprehenſions ſo darkned and bewildered, that we are apt to read</hi> Pſalm 110. 1. thus, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſit thou at my Right Hand.</hi> And John 3. 16. <hi>God ſo loved the World that he ſent himſelf: and many others would come under the like Abſurdities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35672:13"/>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> This is ſuch a confuſed heap of Words, that I know not well where to begin. Firſt, If by Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt he mean as I do; <hi>i. e.</hi> That though he were a Man, yet he was alſo Truly God by Nature, then I am of his Mind: But then he doth not truly repreſent the Quakers Notion, for they ſay he is <hi>only God,</hi> and <hi>not Man</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>2. If he means as they do, <hi>That he is only God;</hi> then I wonder at his confidence, to throw that abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity upon others, which lies only at the door of the Quakers, Ranters, Muggletonians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and how he, and they, conjoyned, can remove it, I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; but am of Opinion, That if <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> had one of them the Strength of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and the other the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> they might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves all their life-time, and yet find it a difficulty too hard for them to reſolve. But however, I know they are Men of confidence, and will venture upon hard things; I will therefore try their ſtrength and skill in this Matter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>W. L.</hi> tells us, <hi>We being taught that Chriſt is the very</hi> Jehovah, <hi>Creator or Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it doth ſo bewilder our Apprehenſions, that we are apt to read</hi> Pſalm 110. 1. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. and John 3. 16. <hi>God ſo loved the World that he ſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which he ſaith is an Abſurdity;</hi> And I think a great one too: But that it lies not at our doors, but at the Quakers; I think it no hard thing to prove: and in order thereunto, I would ask theſe few Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether <hi>W. L.</hi> ever heard any Man of <hi>T. H's</hi> Opinion about Chriſt, i. e. <hi>That he is both God and Man, and a Diſtinct Perſon without us,</hi> affirm, That in reſpect of his Perſon he was only Jehovah, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35672:14"/>
or Father (as he is pleaſed to word it) and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſayable from their own Principles? when at the ſame time they alſo affirm, <hi>That he is truly Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the Quakers do not deny that the ſame Body which Chriſt had when he was upon the Earth, and is now aſcended with into Heaven, is a Part of that Chriſt, and affirm it to be <hi>only a Body in which he was, and acted in for a time here upon Earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the Quakers do not believe <hi>That it is only the Light or Spirit which was in that Man which is the Chriſt,</hi> which Spirit (they ſay) is now in them and all Men?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether it will not thence follow that the Quakers believe Chriſt <hi>to be only God?</hi> if they deny it, I am able to prove it againſt them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether the Quakers do not <hi>deny all Perſonal Diſtinction</hi> between the Father and the Son, and ſay, that the Son is the Father, and the Father is a Son to himſelf?</p>
               <p>If the Quakers ſhould deny this and ſay, <hi>There is a Diſtinction of Perſons in the Divine Eſſence; Will. Penn</hi> may remember what himſelf hath written in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch a Diſtinction in his Book, Entituled, <hi>The Sandy Foundation ſhaken;</hi> where among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayings of that import, he lays down this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove that Doctrine <hi>Abſurd</hi> and <hi>Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If each Perſon be God, and God ſubſiſts in three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then in each Perſon there are three Perſons or Gods, and ſo from three they would encreaſe to nine, and ſo in infinitum:</hi> from whence it is plain the Quakers deny all Diſtinction of Perſons in the Divine Eſſence.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35672:14"/>
6. Having gained thus far upon them, I therefore query, Whether according to their own Opinion this abſurdity will not neceſſarily fall upon them, to read thoſe Scriptures as <hi>W. L.</hi> hath done; <hi>That the Lord ſaid to himſelf, ſit thou on my Right Hand;</hi> and that <hi>he ſo loved the World, that he ſent himſelf:</hi> and all other Scriptures of the like import, as that where he ſaith; <hi>If I bear witneſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true. There is another which beareth witneſs of me. The Father himſelf which hath ſent me, hath born witneſs of me,</hi> John 5. 31, 32, 37. which they muſt read, <hi>If I bedr witneſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true,</hi> But <hi>I bear witneſs of my ſelf:</hi> and then how bravely will they make the <hi>Lip of Truth</hi> to contradict himſelf<hi>:</hi> and indeed make void the Fathers Teſtimony concerning his Son, and make it doubtful whether he be the True Meſſiah?</p>
               <p>If they aſſert it, it's horrid Blaſphemy, and the very Opinion of <hi>Muggleton</hi> and his Company, who they ſay are Impoſtors; for they agree with the Quakers in this, <hi>That there is no diſtinction of Perſons in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence:</hi> and therefore they ſay, <hi>That the Son was the Father, and the Father the Son; and that when Chriſt died, God himſelf died.</hi> But the Quakers, though they agree with them in the former, yet they differ in the latter; For the Quakers ſay. <hi>That Chriſt in reſpect of himſelf never died,</hi> neither could he, becauſe he was <hi>only God,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do therefore begg of theſe two Gentlemen <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> to ſhew us how it is poſſible for them to extricate themſelves out of this difficulty, and that they would either remove this abſurdity from the Quakers door, or elſe acknowledg they have been miſtaken in charging their own Guilt upon other Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35672:15"/>
In the next place, <hi>W. L.</hi> tells us, <hi>And ſo I paſs to the Humanity,</hi> and makes a full ſtop, only in the Margin, or rather a Break that is made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; he puts in theſe words, <hi>I know no better Text to teach us the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt, than</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 27, 28.</p>
               <p>Reader, If this be a paſſing to the Humanity, no Man ever paſt from it (as I think) with that brevity before; if this be an account of the Humanity, I muſt confeſs I don't underſtand it: but let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe two Verſes he hath quoted for our informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>For he hath put all things under his Feet: but when he ſaith all things are put under him, it is manifeſt that he is excepted that did put all things under him.</hi> ver. 28. <hi>And when all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him, then ſhall the Son alſo himſelf be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi> Which words I have ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and I find nothing in them to the purpoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, <hi>i. e.</hi> to prove the <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> of Chriſt with that Cleerneſs <hi>W. L.</hi> ſpeaks of: But I think I have found out his intent; namely, to lead us from the Matter we are upon. But I will exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his next words, which are theſe:</p>
               <p>W. L. <hi>Only with this Caution that becauſe we op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not our Teachers in theſe Myſteries which are above our Reaſon, we ſuffer not Myſtical</hi> Babylon <hi>to impoſe others upon us contrary to Reaſon; for then we ſhall ſoon be able to give as little Reaſon of the hope that is in us, as the poor</hi> Iriſh-Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> An excellent definition of the Humanity of Chriſt: ſure this Man hath loſt his Wits, or honeſty, or both; but to proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35672:15"/>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> Now (ſaith he) <hi>As to the Quakers denying the Diſtinct Perſon without them, if it were ſo</hi> (is it ſtill but an <hi>If? W. L.</hi> confeſſed at the beginning of this Head, that they did not own it, ſure he hath a bad Memory) <hi>then certainly there is no probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they ſhould be of the Popiſh Pedigree, or ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>reduced to that Religion, as many conceit:</hi> And he gives us a jeer for his Reaſon; i. e. <hi>For that is buſied moſt of all about the Perſon of Chriſt and his Mother too:</hi> and adds, <hi>If the Jeſuites were their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> (as a late printed ſheet would perſwade us) <hi>truly they went as wiſely about their buſineſs, as General</hi> Venables <hi>to take</hi> Hiſpaniola: (and why not Admiral <hi>Penn</hi> too, for I think he was there) <hi>by landing his Army ſo far from it, that before they could get through the Woods, they met ſo many difficulties as forced them to retreat, and aſſault</hi> Jamaica.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I anſwer, That the Quakers might be ſet on work by the Jeſuites, notwithſtanding they deny Chriſt to be a Diſtinct Perſon without them, and the Jeſuites do not: For there is nothing more ſuiting Jeſuitical Policy, than to pretend one thing, and intend another; Their <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> is almoſt as well filled with <hi>Subtilties</hi> and <hi>Equivocations,</hi> as the <hi>Order of Quakers;</hi> and had but this Man ſtudied <hi>Machiavil,</hi> as well as <hi>W. P.</hi> is ſuppoſed to have done, he might get over this Objection with eaſe: For it is poſſible the Jeſuites may deſign the introducing of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> by promoting Quakeriſm: And in my Opinion it's the likelyeſt way to do it, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>the Quakers deny the Holy Scriptures to be a Rule of Faith and Practice to Chriſtians;</hi> and it all <hi>England</hi> were of this mind, what Argument
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35672:16"/>
could be urged againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but what a Jeſuite could eaſily enervate. I have met with divers Popiſh Prieſts in my time, and I always found <hi>Scripture-Argumens the beſt Weapons againſt Popery.</hi> I would not have the Quakers take away from us the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, till they have found a better Sword to put into our hands.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Quakers agree with the Church of Rome, <hi>That there is ſome other infallible Rule of Faith and Practice:</hi> The Quakers uſe to tell us, <hi>It was the Light in every individual man that cometh into the World:</hi> But ſince ſome difference hath hapned among themſelves, which they could not reconcile, <hi>now it is the Spirit in the Body</hi> (as they call it) <hi>that is the Judg in Religious Controverſies.</hi> And can it be thought when the Conteſt ſhall lie here between them and you, that a Jeſuite cannot ſhew better Antiquity and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for his Church, than you can for yours? I ſhould be very ſorry if <hi>Englands</hi> remaining Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, or returning to Popery, depended upon that ſingle iſſue. But to proceed:</p>
               <p n="3">3. But <hi>ſuppoſe the Jeſuites ſhould miſs of their end,</hi> which is to ſuppoſe all that <hi>W. L.</hi> ſuppoſes; this is no Argument to prove, that they may not therefore attempt the doing it; for many men have undertaken things which they could not effect, by reaſon of ſome unhappy and unſeen Accident intervening, and yet their deſign no whit the more impolitickly laid. And why ſhould not <hi>W. L.</hi> think this poſſible, ſeeing at the ſame time he oppoſes it, he brings in the inſtance of General <hi>Venables</hi> to prove <hi>de facto</hi> that ſuch a thing was done: We muſt conclude by this man's Argument, That the Devil will never attempt the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35672:16"/>
doing of an Impoſſibility, in reſpect of the event; and yet if he read but <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. of <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, he will find he did ſo in the Aſſault he made upon our Saviour. And I believe, a Quaker that ſays he hath attained ſuch perfection, that he doth not commit one ſin, cannot ſay but the Devil tempts him to many. Now if the Devil be ſuch a fool to attempt that which is never effected, why may not the Jeſuites do the ſame? For I always thought the Devil was too cunning for a Jeſuite, and I doubt they will find it ſo too at the laſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But why doth <hi>W. L.</hi> make ſuch a ſtir about this Book, called, <hi>The Quakers Pedigree?</hi> I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion there is ſome wit, if not much truth contained therein: But why doth he inſinuate, as if the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts made it, and as if they promoted it? This muſt needs be to render them ridiculous, which is a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy deſign. But to prevent him from perſevering therein for the future, I will tell him what the man is not which made that Book, <hi>HE is not one of the People called Baptiſts:</hi> I could let him know who did write it, but I will not humour him ſo far at this time, becauſe he hath ſo pleaſed himſelf to throw dirt upon us in Print about it; for which he deſerves a ſharper Reproof, than I will permit my pen to give him at this time: <hi>Will. Pen,</hi> who ſeems to have dipt his quill in Gall and Wormwood, may do that piece of Juſtice for me, if he pleaſe.</p>
               <p>But ſaid <hi>W. L. Why ſhould we think they deny the Perſon of Chriſt? it is not long ſince they were railed on as the Spawn of</hi> SOCINUS, <hi>for denying the Divinity, and now they are faced about to oppoſe his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity? either they are very unſettled, or</hi> T. H. <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtands them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35672:17"/>
Anſw. <hi>Will. Luddington</hi> is no ſooner got out of General <hi>Venables</hi> Wood, but he is got into one him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: But I'le do that kindneſs for him as the Law required (when a man ſaw his neighbours Ox, or Aſs going aſtray) to bring him home if I can.</p>
               <p>There is a man hath written a Book very lately, entituled, <hi>The Chriſtian, a Quaker; The Quaker a Chriſtian:</hi> Which they ſeem to glory in very much, and do him the kindneſs to ſell his Books. And one Reaſon he gives to prove, that the name of a Chriſtian doth moſt properly belong to a Quaker is this, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Quaker is an Aſs:</hi> His words are theſe,</p>
               <p>He being before ſpeaking of <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Diſciples were there firſt called</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that is to ſay, Chriſt's Aſſes:</hi> And in a break made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he inſerts theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Aſſes;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chriſt's Aſſes,</hi> page 23, 24. And continuing his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon this ſubject, in the latter end of <hi>p.</hi> 25. and beginning of <hi>p.</hi> 26. he hath theſe words:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But theſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>whom this Author calls Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> (meaning <hi>T. H.) walk by a better Rule; for if they receive a Blow on the one Cheek, they turn to them that give it the other alſo (ſo they profeſs) patiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing all manner of Affronts, Perſecutions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and Revilings, returning not evil for evil, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Commandment of the Everlaſting God: So that they may truly enough be termed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chriſt's Aſſes.</hi> To which I anſwer:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This Author doth abuſe his unlearned Reader; for that word in the 11th of <hi>Acts</hi> verſ. 26. is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Which the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica Sacra,</hi> p. 288. renders thus, <hi>Qui Chriſti diſcipulum ſe profitetur, &amp; à Chriſto ſe denominat;</hi> Who profeſſes themſelves Diſciples of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35672:17"/>
Chriſt, and derive their name from Chriſt. And it is ſo uſed alſo in <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 28. and in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 16. both quoted by the ſaid Learned Author.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe we ſhould interpret the word as the Quakers Advocate doth, then we muſt read <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 28. thus, <hi>Almoſt thou perſwadeſt me to be one of Chriſt's Aſſes;</hi> and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>But if any man ſuffer as one of Chriſt's Aſſes, let him not be aſhamed.</hi> But how ridiculous this would be, I leave to all that hold the name of Chriſtian as Venerable to determine: If this will not make a Quaker to bluſh, what will?</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, Beſides thoſe he mentions, I am perſwaded he conſulted as his Oracle in this point, <hi>that famous Conjurer</hi> Cornelius Agrippa, who at the end of his Book, called, <hi>The vanity of Sciences, gives the like ridiculous account of a Chriſtian, by comparing him to an Aſs.</hi> But what have the Quakers gained by this man's Book? He hath proved them to be Aſſes, and he that took them to be otherwiſe, was miſtaken in them: And I am much afraid I ſhall find one property of an Aſs in <hi>W. L.</hi> which is given by a very Learned Author now living; his words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> An Aſs; <hi>ſome way or other</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it ſeems to be a troubleſome Beaſt by its name; for the root is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>he was troubleſome, and ſo any Aſs</hi> (tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Davus aliquis, perturbat omnia) <hi>troubleth all where he cometh.</hi> But let the trouble be as great as it will, I will go on to proſecute my purpoſe, and perform my promiſe, to bring him out of this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth, if I can.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>They railed on them as the Spawn of</hi> SOCINUS, <hi>for denying the Divinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35672:18"/>
2. <hi>But now</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>they are faced about to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Humanity:</hi> From whence he draws this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>Either they are very unſettled, or</hi> T. H. <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtands them.</hi> And till this <hi>Dilemma</hi> be removed, it ſeems <hi>W. L.</hi> can't go forward: If this be the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, I'le do him that kindneſs to remove it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I do affirm, That in this point <hi>T. H.</hi> doth not miſunderſtand them; <hi>for the Quakers do ſay, That Chriſt is not a diſtinct Perſon without us.</hi> Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head <hi>in</hi> Dip. pl. p. 13. ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt a Perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us is not Scripture Language; but the Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphites, and Muggletonians. The Socinians tell us of a perſonal Chriſt, and that the Man Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, hath in Heaven a place remote from Earth, a Humane body. But doth he believe him to be the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, whilſt he imagines him to be a perſonal Chriſt? a Humane body ſo limited and confined to a remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Geo. Whitehead, <hi>Append. to Reaſ. againſt Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> p. 21. Therefore you ſee the difficulty lies not here.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any perſons did rail on them as the Spawn of <hi>Socinus,</hi> for denying the Divinity, I ſuppoſe they were miſtaken. But ſuppoſe they ſhould have ſaid, they held that part of <hi>Socinus</hi> Doctrine, that ſaith, <hi>Chriſt gave no plenary Satisfaction to the Juſtice of God for the ſins of men,</hi> herein they had not wronged them: For while <hi>the Quakers believe Chriſt to be only God, he is not capable to ſuffer death;</hi> it being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to imagine, that the Deity can become Mortal: And becauſe <hi>they deny the Body to be a part of the Chriſt,</hi> they are forced to ſay, <hi>Chriſt never died,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, <hi>he did not ſatisfie Juſtice thereby.</hi> So that <hi>W. L.</hi> may ſee, that the Quakers are not faced about to oppoſe the Humanity, for they always oppoſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35672:18"/>
it; neither is <hi>T. H.</hi> miſtaken about their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Well, I perceive <hi>W. L.</hi> is got half-way out of this Labyrinth; for in his next words he ſaith, <hi>Let's be charitable in theſe Myſterious points however, and expound theſe Extreams as we do that betwixt</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> James, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> Rom. 4. <hi>with</hi> James 2. <hi>for as Faith and Works, ſo Divinity and Humanity muſt go together.</hi> And what God hath joyned, let no man put aſunder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I wiſh the Quakers would but do ſo, and then this Controverſie would ſoon be ended. As to what he tells me of <hi>W. P.</hi> his words at the <hi>Barbican-Meeting,</hi> as an inſtance, I ſay this to it, When <hi>W. P.</hi> hath given us ſome infallible Demonſtration, that he did not ſpeak equivocally in thoſe Expreſſions, then, and not till then, do they deſerve my cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, any further, than to anſwer him in the words of the Roman Orator, <hi>Quid attinet glorioſe loqui, niſi conſtanter loquare;</hi> Cic. l. 2. de Fin. p. 61. <hi>For what availeth it for a man to ſpeak gloriouſly, if he be not conſtant, and ſticks not firmly unto that which he ſpeaketh.</hi> And I fear I may ſay of him, as it's ſaid of ſome others by <hi>Auguſtine, Hoc in labiis, non in corde dicere.</hi> Aug. Epiſt. 20. Tom. 2. p. 588. <hi>They ſpeak it but with their lips, they believe it not with their hearts.</hi> But let us proceed to the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="principle">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35672:19"/>
               <head>4. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe fourth Charge is (ſaith he,) <hi>That Chriſt Redeemed himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>This our Friend</hi> T. H. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to be but his own Conſequence from their words, which he leaves to the judgment of others, (as indeed all Conſequences ought to be:) And I'le tell you what my weak apprehenſion is of it, The ſayings from whence he hath drawn this Charge, I confeſs are above my capacity: I do not underſtand, how Chriſt is both the Election, and the Elect Seed: Nor how</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's <hi>old decayed Body, was a Type of the Seed of Abraham.</hi> Now I begin to like my Author, and I ſhould have done ſo before, if he had ſpoke as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly: I wiſh he may keep in this mind. A little after he ſaith, W. P. <hi>aſſerts the Redemption of the Seed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But then he endeavours to extenuate the fault, ſaying, <hi>It's true, it looks with a ſtrange countenance to us, but yet there is ſome of even the very ſame in Scripture; as that in</hi> Iſa. 59. 16. He wondred there was no Interceſſor; therefore his own Arm brought Salvation to him: <hi>And in</hi> Chap. 63. 5. Mine own Arm brought Salvation unto me, and my fury it upheld me. Whence faith <hi>W. P.</hi> in <hi>Reaſ. againſt Railing, p.</hi> 63. <hi>It is no ways abſurd that we affirm, That the end of Gods manifeſting himſelf in the fleſh, was for the Redemption or Deliverance of his holy life that was in man, as a ſmall ſeed, even the ſmalleſt of ſeeds that had been long vex'd, grieved and preſſed down by ſin and iniquity:</hi> And in page 64. <hi>This Seed was, and is pure for ever.</hi> Here, ſaith <hi>W. L. He</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35672:19"/>
                  <hi>tells what he means by Redemption of the Seed.</hi> In this he hath fully cleared <hi>T. H.</hi> from the guilt of Forgery: And I will alſo quit this point, when I have conſidered the meaning of thoſe two Texts urged to prove it, or rather to excuſe <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I take notice, That though <hi>W. P.</hi> and the Quakers deny the Scriptures to be a Rule, yet they can make uſe of them in favour of themſelves, when they think they will ſerve for their purpoſe: But to paſs that.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is obvious to all that will take the pains to conſider them, that theſe Texts do not prove what they are brought for; i. e. <hi>That the end of Chriſt's coming was to redeem himſelf:</hi> For as there is no ſuch words ſpoken by the Prophet, ſo it is contrary to the general ſcope and deſign of the Goſpel, and to the expreſs words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 15. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, That Chriſt Jeſus came into the World to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief:</hi> And that he came to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt; not <hi>a loſt God,</hi> and <hi>a loſt Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Geo. Keith</hi> ſaith, but <hi>loſt</hi> and undone <hi>ſinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If you will have my underſtanding of theſe two Scriptures, it is this; That by Salvation is meant by a figure the perſon ſaved, and that it ſignifies no more, but that he purchaſed them to himſelf, the Abſtract being there put for the Concrete, as is uſual in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is put for <hi>the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons circumciſed;</hi> and in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. <hi>Helps, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,</hi> is put for <hi>Helpers and Governors,</hi> with many more of the like kind that might be mentioned: And therefore it's ſaid in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 6. <hi>I alſo will give thee for a Light to the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the ends of the earth;</hi> that is, My Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35672:20"/>
that I have appointed for them. For God, who is always perfectly happy, and Bleſſedneſs it ſelf, cannot ſtand in need of any Salvation; yea, it is as great an abſurdity as any the Quakers can be guilty of, to affirm it. But from hence we may ſee, that the Light which is in them, doth teach them to have ſtrange blaſphemous thoughts of God; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of the abundance of their hearts their mouths do utter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="principle">
               <head>5. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe fifth Charge is, <hi>That the Quakers do deny the Scriptures to be the Rule of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice unto Chriſtians.</hi> And <hi>T. H.</hi> brings in <hi>W. P.</hi> his words for proof<hi>:</hi> Which are theſe,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We deny the Scriptures to be the Rule of Faith and Practice; In honour to that Divine-Light that was the Author of them.</hi> W. P. <hi>in</hi> Reaſ. againſt Rail. page 48.</p>
               <p>W. L. <hi>The Quakers ſayings brought to prove this, I confeſs at a diſtance, or to a haſty, or a prejudiced Reader ſeem to do it; but look ſeriouſly and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly on them, and there is as much truth in them as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Ben. Furly</hi> ſays, <hi>There is nothing in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that is a duty upon him, or which he is obliged to obey, becauſe there recorded; and ſo ſay I.</hi> He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledgeth, that <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> ſaith, <hi>That it is Idolatry to call the Bible the means of our knowing God,</hi> Dip. pl. p. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Reader, <hi>W. L.</hi> hath gone very far already towards the clearing <hi>T. H.</hi> But hear what he ſaith further, <hi>page</hi> 17. he there confeſſes, <hi>They ſeem to him and others to ſpeak ſlightly of the Scriptures,</hi> which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35672:20"/>
(ſaith he) <hi>I would not have them do.</hi> But it ſeems they will not be ruled by him; for you have heard <hi>W. P.</hi> his poſitive denial already. And for <hi>Ben. Furly,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>It is the greateſt errour in the World, that ever was invented, and the ground of all error, to affirm, That the Scripture ought to be a Rule to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: Whatſoever is a command to me, I muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from any man or thing without me; nay, not the Scripture it ſelf.</hi> And <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> in his Works, <hi>p.</hi> 62. ſaith, <hi>He that perſwades people to let the Scriptures be the Rule of Faith and Practice, would keep people in darkneſs.</hi> Now I hope <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger.</p>
               <p>But whereas my Author doth endeavour to cover their nakedneſs by ſome pitiful Evaſions that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of his is too narrow, the Light in every man doth ſee their folly, and is above them; juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them by the Light of the Holy Scriptures, which they do wickedly reject: And their great pretences to Light and Knowledg, are ſeen to be the manifeſt effects of Darkneſs and Ignorance. <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony,</hi> becauſe they ſpeak againſt this Word, there can be no Light in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. W. L.</hi> askes this Queſtion, <hi>What Scriptures do they diſown for a Rule, but ſuch as relate to ſome external parts of Worſhip? and do not we our ſelves do the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, They deny the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> yea, as <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> phraſes it (as quoted by <hi>W. L.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) the <hi>BIBLE,</hi> which contains all the Books of holy Scripture both in the Old and New-Teſtament, <hi>to be a Rule;</hi> and therefore tis idle for him to talk as if it were ſome part of it only, that related to external Worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35672:21"/>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But ſaith <hi>W. L. Do not we our ſelves do the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is one thing I would be ſatisfied in, what <hi>W. L.</hi> means by ſaying, <hi>WE, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R</hi> in this Diſcourſe? I ſuppoſe he doth it on purpoſe to inſinuate, as if himſelf were a Baptiſt, becauſe he hath been ſo ſome years ago: If that be his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then I muſt tell him, it's unbecoming a man profeſſing Religion ſo to carry it; for I do declare, That he hath not had Communion with any Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Church in <hi>England,</hi> nor been owned by them, as worthy their Communion, for ſeveral years, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he hath gone to any place where he is unknown, and got it ſurreptitiouſly; which I think the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod uſed in ſuch caſes, among our Churches, will hardly admit him to do<hi>:</hi> And to my knowledg, they have refuſed long ago to admit him to preach among them, becauſe of his corrupt and dangerous Principles. And yet the chief of the Quakers in a ſcurrilous Book of theirs, in the Title-page, call him <hi>a Sober Baptiſt Preacher;</hi> ſignifying to the World, that he is owned ſo now, which is a moſt abominable untruth. But they ſeem to have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Truth and Honeſty, neither with their Tongues nor Penns: For as Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> ſheweth in his Queſtions for the Quakers, <hi>That two of theſe Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers,</hi> i. e. <hi>William Mead,</hi> and <hi>John Oſgood, have both of them</hi> (with others) <hi>took their Oaths in</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, <hi>one before Sir</hi> William Beverſham, and the other before Sir <hi>William Child;</hi> and yet it's known to all, that this is the Quakers avowed Principle, <hi>That it is ſinful to ſwear at all,</hi> or in any caſe: For as <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> ſaith in his Catechiſm, quoted by Mr. <hi>Ives, p.</hi> 107. <hi>All that ſwear are out of the Power of Jeſus</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:35672:21"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt and his Truth, and the Doctrine of the Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>AND ARE FALSE CHRISTIANS,</hi> &amp;c. Now though they can rail againſt others at pleaſure, yet if we do but tell them of their faults, though it be with the greateſt mildneſs that may be, they preſently fall a raging and raving, as if they were poſſeſt with, and under the power of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Spirit. I will therefore leave them, and return to <hi>W. L.</hi> whom I know to be a man that hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to, and contended for the Quakers Principles for divers years: And I would ſay thus much to <hi>W. L.</hi> by way of advice, That he would <hi>either be what he pretends to be, or profeſs to be what he is.</hi> Why doſt thou halt between two Opinions? Be in earneſt, and don't trifle thus about Religion. God is a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, and he is very angry with <hi>Lukewarm Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> but more with <hi>Apoſtates.</hi> Take heed to thy ſelf, and to the Holy Scriptures; <hi>for thereby thou mayeſt be made wiſe to Salvation,</hi> through faith in Chriſt: And if thou ſhalt reject the ſame, know of a truth, that Gods Word will certainly ſtand againſt thee for evil; for I perceive thou haſt drunk down too large a draught of their poyſonous Doctrines, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in this very inſtance under conſideration (beſides many other;) for thou ſayeſt, <hi>There is as much truth in this Poſition, That the Scriptures are no Rule of Faith and Practice unto Chriſtians, as thou deſireſt.</hi> Where is then the difference between <hi>W. L.</hi> and a Quaker? But we ſhall find much more of this in his Book.</p>
               <p>There is ſome other rambling nonſenſical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe under this head, which I ſhall paſs with this Obſervation upon it:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:35672:22"/>
1. That <hi>W. L.</hi> confeſſes <hi>T. H's.</hi> Charges, are <hi>matters of Opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>We read of no puniſhment denounced againſt men, nor rewards given for their Opinions at the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That if <hi>W. L.</hi> hath no reward from the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, for this ſervice he hath done for them, <hi>in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending about Opinions,</hi> he is like to have none in the laſt day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That a man may hold and maintain the moſt wicked and abominable <hi>Opinions</hi> that are in the World, though never ſo Atheiſtical and Antichriſtian, <hi>and not be condemned for it at the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſure <hi>W. L.</hi> forgets, The corrupt Principles, lead to corrupt Practices; as he will certainly find this corrupt Principle will do (if proſecuted) <hi>in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Scriptures to be a Rule of Faith and Practice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do but debauch a mans Conſcience with wicked Principles, and you will quickly ſee him a man of a debauched Converſation. Why doth God appoint the Goſpel to be preached? Surely, beſides its Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the revelation of himſelf and Son; it is, that by it we might come to have an evil opinion of the ways of ſin, and ſo forſake them: And by preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God therein as an Holy God, and the Beauty, Glory, and Excellency of Holineſs, we might come to have our minds influenced thereby, fall into a love and liking of it, which begets holy Principles in us, and ſo leads us to a holy Life. And herein lies much of that difference, betwixt the obedience of a man that is meerly Moral, and one that is Evangelical: The one being taught by the Law of Nature, doth that which is good for the matter of it; the other,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35672:22"/>
as he is farther enlightned, doth not only obey in doing more, but in all the parts of his obedience he acts <hi>from higher Principles,</hi> and to <hi>a more noble end.</hi> But whileſt others are ſlighting good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, I deſire to prize and improve them for the honour of God, and my own Salvation; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey as God hath commanded in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="principle">
               <head>6. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſixth charge is, <hi>That the ſpeaking of the Spirit in any, is of greater Authority than the Scriptures. W. L.</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>There is no reaſon in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for this Charge; for the ſaying brought to prove it is thus, That which was ſpoken from the Spirit of Truth in any, is of as great Authority as the Scriptures, (and Chapters are) and greater.</hi> Geo. Whitehead's Serious Apol. <hi>p.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> A man may ſee how dark the eyes of this mans underſtanding are become, that he ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, <hi>that</hi> G. W. <hi>ſpeaks the very words that</hi> T. H. <hi>charges upon them,</hi> and yet can ſee no reaſon for this Charge: But I hope he can ſee that this proves <hi>T. H</hi> to be no Forger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> Having confeſſed the Charge, he goes to excuſe it by ſaying, <hi>That the addition of theſe words,</hi> [and greater] <hi>will eaſily make any moderate man to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> G. W. <hi>means in ſome caſes it may be greater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Queſtion that was put will inform us of his meaning; i. e. <hi>Do you eſteem of your ſpeakings to be of as great Authority as any Chapter in the BIBLE?</hi> Now both theſe words are in the Quakers Anſwer, <hi>Of as great Authority as the Scriptures (and</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35672:23"/>
                  <hi>Chapters) are, and greater;</hi> though <hi>W. L.</hi> hath the civility to leave out <hi>(and chapters are)</hi> I know not for what cauſe, unleſs it were to introduce that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance he gives, on purpoſe to evade the force of <hi>T. H.</hi> his evidence: But I will not let it ſlip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>And that we cannot deny! for if one of</hi> T. H. <hi>or</hi> I. G<hi>'s. Sermons, ſhould at any time make a greater impreſſion upon you or I, than ever any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did; may we not lawfully ſay, That the Spirit of Truth ſpeaking in either of theſe men, was of greater Authority to us, that is, wrought more powerfully upon us by them, than by the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I would make this anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>W. L.</hi> miſtakes the Queſtion exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for it's not about <hi>the influence,</hi> but <hi>the Authority,</hi> which the Scripture hath over us <hi>as a Rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>W. L.</hi> ſuppoſes by theſe expreſſions, that <hi>T. H.</hi> and <hi>I. G.</hi> do not expound the Holy Scriptures in their Sermons: Which is a falſe Suppoſition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And from thence he concludes, That the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences their Sermons have upon the Conſciences of their Auditors, is not from the Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God's Word, but of their own ſayings.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas he ſuppoſes, <hi>the Spirit of Truth ſpeaks by theſe men:</hi> I readily grant it, but not excluſive of, but in conjunction with the Doctrine they preach, agreeable to the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Therefore I conclude, That whatever good effect their Doctrine hath upon the Souls of men, for their Converſion and Salvation, it is wrought by thoſe words they deliver unto us; not as they are <hi>the words of men</hi> taken abſtractedly (for as ſuch, they can have no ſuch Efficacie) <hi>but as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Word of God, which effectually worketh in</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35672:23"/>
                  <hi>them that believe.</hi> Thus all men may ſee this inſtance ſerves not to the purpoſe for which he intended it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But ſaith W. L. <hi>What need we fear any dangerous Conſequences attending this ſaying? ſo long as they agree with us in this, That every Spirit ſpeaking contrary to plain Scripture is falſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This man is very apt in drawing fale ſSup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: <hi>Do the Quakers that deny the Scriptures to be a Rule of Faith and Practice, make it the Standard to try Spirits by? and conclude all to be falſe that ſpeak contrary thereunto?</hi> No, if they had done that, or would yet do it, they would ſee themſelves to be <hi>falſe Teachers, no Chriſtians,</hi> but <hi>Impoſtors:</hi> Their Principles and Practices being contrary to Holy Scripture, and the Rule of Chriſtianity therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="principle">
               <head>7. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Seventh Charge is, <hi>That is no Command from God to me, which God hath given by way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to another: Neither did any of the Saints act by the Command which was to another. Every one obeyed their own Command.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>There is no great difficulty nor dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in this; for it's very true in one ſenſe, and as falſe in another, and Charity will always take the beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> There is ſo great danger in it, that it leaves all men without a Rule for their Faith and Practice: For if I am to obey none of thoſe Commands given by God to others, and recorded in Scripture for our Inſtruction; and there be no new Revelation for the Rule of my Faith and Practice, then are all men whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of a Rule; and yet this is the very caſe.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35672:24"/>
And whereas he would ſalve it, by diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one Command and another, and allowing the Quakers a liberty to pick and chuſe, obey what they liſt, and leave the reſt undone: This may not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Quakers themſelves; for they confeſs, that the Scriptures were all given forth by the ſame Spirit, and therefore muſt needs be of equal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in thoſe Commands they enjoyn upon us as our duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> I know no Objection lies againſt this, but the Quakers affirming, <hi>They have immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for the Rule of their Faith and Practice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, It's eaſie to affirm any thing: But that they cannot prove it is evident, not only from the want of ſufficient Teſtimony at all times, when they have been deſired to prove it; but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, for that at the late Diſpute in their own Meeting-houſe in <hi>Wheelers-ſtreet,</hi> they were not able to give any other Demonſtration of it, <hi>but what a Turk or Impoſtor might give, or pretend too, equal with them.</hi> But if they think they can do it; when they have further conſulted one another about it, I will give them a longer time, that they may fetch in what other Auxiliaries they have: for I perceive the Light within them cannot ſupply them with ſufficient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration; for if it could, they had that to have been <hi>Geo Keith's</hi> Dictator in <hi>Wheelers-ſtreet.</hi> In the mean time I would ask <hi>W. L.</hi> a few Queſtions upon his Diſtinction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Why he ſhould ſay, <hi>That the Quakers, except againſt ſome particular Commands, as not belonging to them; as that Command to the Jews, To anoint their heads when they faſted; that to the young man, To ſell all, and give to the poor; and that to</hi> Paul, <hi>To go to</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35672:24"/>
                  <hi>Rome.</hi> Whereas it's manifeſt, the Quakers ſay, <hi>That not any one of the Commands in Scripture concern them:</hi> That the Scripture is no Rule to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why he ſhould ſay, <hi>That no Quaker will ſay theſe Commands,</hi> Swear not at all, Love your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Quench not the Spirit, <hi>&amp;c. concerns not them, becauſe they were ſpoken to others.</hi> Whereas he knows, they do ſo confidently affirm, <hi>That thoſe are no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to them, that were given by God to others, and recorded in the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Scripture be no Rule, how comes the Quaker to know, that it is <hi>a ſin to Swear,</hi> and a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue <hi>not to Swear at all?</hi> He muſt not ſay, Becauſe 'tis written in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> for that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was given to thoſe that lived 1600 years ago; and therefore that can be no Command to them: For <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> ſaith in his works, <hi>page</hi> 47. <hi>That is no Command from God to me, which he commands to another: Neither did any of the Saints we read of in Scripture, act by the Command which was to another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They obeyed every one their own Command.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If it be a ſin as the Quaker ſaith, <hi>To take any Oath,</hi> how comes it then to paſs, that the Quakers do frequently go to Law with their Neighbours, and employ men, yea, give them money to come in and ſwear for them: And alſo, when others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be accepted in their ſtead, <hi>Why do ſome of the chief Quakers in</hi> London <hi>take Oaths themſelves?</hi> Surely if your Principle be true, both theſe Practices are Abomination to the Lord. Now with what face of Truth or Honeſty can theſe men cenſure others, and do the ſame things themſelves?</p>
               <p n="5">5. How can the Quakers tell what Spirit it is they muſt receive, muſt not quench the motions of,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35672:25"/>
muſt be taught and inſtructed by, and that thoſe things it teaches them are true? What Rule is there to diſtinguiſh it from all falſe Spirits? that ſo all men may know what Spirit they are to follow, and what to reject: <hi>If theſe things be not diſcovered by the Light of the Holy Scriptures, how can they be known?</hi> If they muſt be examined by the Light thereof? then the Scriptures muſt be acknowledged to be our Rule, and the Commands therein binding to us, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that the Quakers ſay to the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="principle">
               <head>8. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Eighth Charge is, <hi>That Juſtification by that Righteouſneſs which Chriſt fulfilled for us, wholly without us, is a Doctrine of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. P</hi>'s. Anſwer is thus, <hi>And indeed this we deny, (viz.</hi> Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt fulfilled in his own Perſon for us, wholly without us<hi>:) And boldly affirm it in the name of the Lord, to be a Doctrine of Devils, and an Arm of the Sea of Corruption, which doth now Deluge the World.</hi> Will. Penn. <hi>Serious Apol. p.</hi> 148.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Will. Lud.</hi> ſaith, <hi>This makes a great noiſe; ſurely ſomewhat more than ordinary moved</hi> W. P. <hi>to write at this rate:</hi> Herein he confeſſes the Charge, ſo that <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger.</p>
               <p>But firſt (ſaith <hi>W. L.) let us calmly conſider the terms,</hi> whereupon he doth expreſs himſelf in favour of <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L. This one word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſerves for Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Righteouſneſs all along the New-Teſtament; ſo that when we are ſaid to be juſtified, it is all one in my underſtanding as to be made juſt or righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:35672:25"/>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> I will ſpeak ſomething to this, before I proceed any further: And firſt, whereas he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſerves for Juſtification and Righteouſneſs all along the New-Teſtament;</hi> I hope he doth not intend, that there is no other words uſed to expreſs it by; for I think that word is but ſeldom uſed in the New-Teſtament upon that occaſion, but moſt frequently other words to expreſs the Spirits mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Therefore being juſtified by faith,</hi> verſ. 16. it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>But the free gift is of many offences unto Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> v. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>unto Juſtification of life.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica Sacra p.</hi> 69. ſaith thus upon that very word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Juſtitia, i. e.</hi> Juſtice; in which ſenſe he ſaith, <hi>the word is often uſed,</hi> and brings in <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, <hi>Juſtitia ea quae eſt in nobis;</hi> and a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Eſt ipſa animi integritas, ſanctitas, &amp; innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, per quam ſancti vivimus &amp; placemus Deo vel bonis viris.</hi> So that it muſt be underſtood, <hi>to reſpect that Integrity, Holineſs and Innocency of the ſouls of good men, by which they live a holy life, and pleaſe God.</hi> But this cannot be done, without their perſons be firſt acquitted of their former ſins, by the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they receive from Chriſt through believing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. But here I do diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſo as to obey perfectly all that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires at all times, both in thought, word and deed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An <hi>Evangelical Righteouſneſs,</hi> which is a ſincere endeavour of the Soul to do all that God requires; although by reaſon of the pravity of his nature, he cannot attain it; which is accepted with God for Chriſts ſake, as if he had perfectly done it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35672:26"/>
3. And <hi>that Righteouſneſs which Chriſt fulfilled for us in his own Perſon, wholly without us;</hi> which was his keeping the Law perfectly <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> and his ſuffering death for our ſins, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 3. <hi>Chriſt died for O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R ſins according to the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this is <hi>imputed to us, if we believe,</hi> Rom. 4. 5, 6, 7, 8. &amp; 22, 23, 24, 25. And Chriſt is <hi>made unto us Righteouſneſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 30. And in this ſenſe he is called, <hi>The Lord O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 23. 6. And therefore it's ſaid, <hi>Chriſt was made ſin for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. <hi>ult. He bare O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R ſins in his own body on the tree,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 24. The truth is, if Legal Righteouſneſs, and Juſtification <hi>THRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH</hi> Chriſt, according to the Goſpel, be the ſame thing, then the Quaker is right <hi>in denying Juſtification by that Righteouſneſs Chriſt fulfilled for us,</hi> both Active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Paſſively, <hi>in his own Perſon, wholly without us:</hi> But then the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was miſtaken, who ſaith, <hi>A man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt: Even we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified—for if Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs come by the Law, then Chriſt is dead in vain, Gal.</hi> 2. 16, 21. But by this I perceive, That the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers rather than they will own Juſtification by that Righteouſneſs Chriſt fulfilled for us, wholly without us, they will avoid that abſurdity laid upon that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by the Apoſtle, i. e. <hi>That then Chriſt died in vain;</hi> by affirming, <hi>That Chriſt, in reſpect of himſelf, never died.</hi> But why I may not from hence conclude, The Quakers profeſſing Chriſtianity to be vain, I know not: If <hi>W. P.</hi> can demonſtrate the contrary,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35672:26"/>
I deſire he would. But let us hear what <hi>W. L.</hi> hath to ſay further touching this thing.</p>
               <p>W. L. <hi>Now that no man can make himſelf ſo, or that he can be ſo without Chriſts Righteouſneſs; and alſo, that this act of juſtifying us, or making us juſt, is of the free Grace of God, through the Redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt, I believe it is granted by us and them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> W. L. mean, according to his former falſe Inſinuation, <hi>the Baptiſts and himſelf,</hi> (though indeed he is not one of that number, neither can he be ſo accounted:) Then I anſwer, That thoſe words expreſſed by him, if as honeſtly intended as plainly expreſt, is that the Baptiſts and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants own. But as I know the Quakers do not own it, I have reaſon to ſuſpect <hi>W. L.</hi> alſo: For in a certain Diſcourſe he had with <hi>R. S.</hi> a good Friend of mine about two years ago, he pleaded for a <hi>ſinleſs Perfection here in this life</hi> (as it's oppoſite to that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, <hi>made Ours by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving)</hi> as the way by which he expected to be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Whereupon <hi>R. S.</hi> asked him, Whether he had yet attained it? <hi>W. L.</hi> told him, <hi>he had not.</hi> Whereupon <hi>R. S.</hi> replied, You do not know, but you may die before you have attained it; how then can you think to ſtand juſtified before God? It cannot be by your own perſonal Righteouſneſs; for that you confeſs you have it not. I ſhould be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to hear him utter ſuch expreſſions, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereunto as theſe are in his Book, but that I conſider he may have learned the Art of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation from <hi>W. P.</hi> by his often converſe with him.</p>
               <p>But now I am upon this Head, I would make ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35672:27"/>
bold as to ask <hi>W. P.</hi> and the Quakers one Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Suppoſe they do attain to a ſtate of ſinleſs Perfection here in this life; yet ſeeing many of them have lived in a courſe of ſinning twenty, thirty, or forty years before they attain it; What muſt make Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for the ſins they have committed in the time paſt of their lives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they ſhall ſay, <hi>Their own Obedience which they perform to the Light within them, after they are thus perfect:</hi> That is to ſuppoſe, the good deeds they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in the latter part of their lives, ſhould make Compenſation for their former evil deeds: Which will proclaim to all intelligent men, not only that they hold Juſtification by their own perſonal Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, excluſive of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, <hi>which is to be juſtified by Works in the ſtricteſt Notion</hi> (being the next Principle we are to enquire into;) but alſo, that they do hold that other Popiſh Principle, To believe that they can do Works of Supererogation. And yet this Author is much diſpleaſed, that any ſhould ſuppoſe <hi>the Quakers do derive their Pedigree from</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> Goes on to excuſe his beloved Friend <hi>W. P.</hi> by telling us, <hi>That foraſmuch as many Teachers ſo word this Doctrine of Juſtification, as the weak are thereby miſled into a vain hope, that God will juſtifie them, or look upon them as juſt and righteous</hi> THROUGH <hi>Chriſt at the laſt day, though they live and die in ſin: Hence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſo great a zeal might ariſe in</hi> W. P. <hi>againſt ſuch Expoſitions of Scripture-Juſtifications and chiefly againſt this phraſe, THRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH CHRIST.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, If <hi>W. P.</hi> hath ſo great a zeal riſen up in him, <hi>CHIEFLY</hi> againſt this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35672:27"/>
phraſe, <hi>THRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH CHRIST:</hi> Then it follows, That if we ſhould word the Doctrine of Juſtification, ſo as to pleaſe <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> we muſt ſay, <hi>That men are juſtified WITHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T CHRIST:</hi> But I hope I ſhall never make that one of the Articles of my Creed.</p>
               <p>But farther <hi>(W. L.</hi> ſaith) <hi>Theſe words,</hi> Wholly without us, <hi>may very well ſatisfie us, That they level not at Scripture-Juſtification, but at our conceits of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Then it ſeems <hi>W. L.</hi> concludes, <hi>That Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by that Righteouſneſs Chriſt fulfilled for us, wholly without us, is not a Doctrine agreeable to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but a conceit.</hi> I perceive now <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger; for <hi>W. L.</hi> doth not only own the words to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>W. P.</hi> but owns the Doctrine of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers about it: And yet forſooth, we muſt be very tender of calling this man a Quaker<hi>:</hi> Howbeit, I conclude, he avoids the name for no other Reaſon, but that he might be the more ſerviceable in propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating their cauſe. An excellent Stratagem!</p>
               <p>As for what he ſaith, <hi>about the Doctrine of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſpringing from the Doctrine of Predeſtination, miſunderſtood, and as held by</hi> Calvin, Beza, Piſcator, Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> &amp;c. As I do not believe it in the ſenſe that I have defined it, and as Proteſtants generally hold it: So for thoſe mens Opinions about the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Abſolute and Irreſpective Reprobation, I ſhall leave it to them whoſe concern it is to clear themſelves of it; for it's none of mine at this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="principle">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:35672:28"/>
               <head>9. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. P.</hi> SAith, His ninth Charge againſt the Quakers is, <hi>That Juſtification is by Works.</hi> Here <hi>W. L.</hi> hath followed his own advice; <hi>viz.</hi> To leave out words moſt material in this Charge: For the words laid down by <hi>T. H.</hi> are;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Quakers hold Juſtification by Works in the ſtricteſt Notion:</hi> And brings theſe proofs out of the Quakers own Books.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God accepts not any, where there is any failing; or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every Demand of Juſtice,</hi> Edw. Burrough's Works, <hi>p.</hi> 33. And in Anſwer to <hi>Queſt.</hi> 14. <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>juſtified by Works? We muſt not conceive that his perſonal Offering, was not a juſtifying Righteouſneſs; but that God was pleaſed to count it ſo. Nor was there any Imputation of anothers Righteouſneſs to</hi> Abraham: <hi>But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, his perſonal Obedience was the ground of that Imputation. Therefore that any ſhould be juſtified by anothers Righteouſneſs imputed, and not inherent in him, is both ridiculous and dangerous.</hi> W. P. Reaſ. againſt Rail. <hi>p.</hi> 80. Now I hope <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger. But let us hear what <hi>W. L.</hi> hath to ſay.</p>
               <p>W. L. <hi>This is almoſt of the ſame nature as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and it's a greatdeal of pity to Heathenize men for preaching up Good-works, eſpecially in a day when they are ſo ſcarce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Rarely well gueſt. Is <hi>T. H.</hi> finding fault with mens preaching up good Works? Surely that's none of the Queſtion: Neither doth he Heathenize any for ſo doing, that's no part of the Charge; nay, he doth not ſo much as mention the words <hi>Heathen,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35672:28"/>
                  <hi>Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Pagan Principle,</hi> in all his twelve Charges. I wonder how <hi>W. L.</hi> did, to give them ſo right a name: The honour of that belongs to himſelf, and not to me nor <hi>T. H.</hi> But ſeeing ſo great a Friend of theirs as <hi>W. L.</hi> is, hath ſo often called them ſo, I hope they will not find fault with me, for writing after his Copy.</p>
               <p>As for what he is pleaſed to ſay, <hi>of his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing meriting by Works; and that he thinks no rational Papiſt can be ſo weak to imagine, that forty or fifty years ſpent all in Good-works, nay forty or fifty thouſand years, can deſerve Eternal Recompence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> is no Argument to the contrary, but that an infatuated Quaker may be of that mind: And why we ſhould not think ſo of them, till they have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves of it, by renouncing <hi>Edw. Burroughs, Will. Penn,</hi> and their Books, with all others, who have aſſerted ſuch Doctrines as theſe, I ſee no Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="principle">
               <head>10. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe tenth Charge is, <hi>That Chriſt fulfilled the Law ONLY as our Patern.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The proof cited by <hi>T. H.</hi> is <hi>W.</hi> P.'s own words, <hi>For not the hearers of the Law are juſt before God: But the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified,</hi> Rom. 2. 13. <hi>From whence</hi> (ſaith <hi>W. P.) how unanſwerably may I obſerve, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs we become doers of that Law, which Chriſt came not to destroy, but as our example to fulfil, we can never be justified before God. Nor let any fancy, that Christ hath ſo fulfilled it for them, as to exclude their obedience from being requiſite to their acceptance, but ONLY as their Patern.</hi> W. P. Sandy Found. <hi>p.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:35672:29"/>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi>'s Reply is, How <hi>T. H.</hi> puts an ill face up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an honeſt Sentence, and repeats <hi>W. P.</hi>'s words as cited by <hi>T. H.</hi> and endeavours, according to his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed manner, to excuſe his great Friend <hi>W. P.</hi> but ſo faintly, that it expires with the breath that names it: And being ſoon ſpent, he concludes in theſe words, <hi>But take it at the worst, as in the Charge, though I will not juſtifie it ſo worded, and underſtood as</hi> T. H. <hi>doth, yet methinks its too harſh to reckon it Heathen Doctrine; I would rather have compared him to</hi> Apollos, <hi>and wiſhing him a little more fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the ends of Chriſts Life and Death, have paſſed it by.</hi> But before I paſs it with you, give me leave to ask a few <hi>Queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Why you ſay, <hi>This is an honeſt Sentence of</hi> W. P. and yet afterwards ſay, <hi>you will not juſtifie it:</hi> Sure you are very inconſiſtent with your ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why you ſay, T. H. <hi>puts an ill face upon it,</hi> when he repeats <hi>W. P.</hi>'s words as you your ſelf do, and as they are in his Book.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Why you ſay, <hi>its too harſh to reckon it Heathen Doctrine,</hi> when the word <hi>Heathen</hi> is not ſo much as mentioned by <hi>T. H.</hi> Sure <hi>W. L.</hi> hath the word <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> by Inſpiration, or elſe he would never hit of it ſo often as he doth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Why <hi>ſhould you compare</hi> Will. Penn <hi>to</hi> Apollos? Do you think him ſo great a man for <hi>Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> when he denies the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> both of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were all for <hi>Baptiſm in water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Why do you ſuppoſe that</hi> W. P. <hi>wants to be more fully inſtructed in the ends of Chriſts Life and Death?</hi> Is it poſſible, that you ſhould imagine <hi>the chief Freacher of,</hi> and <hi>Diſputer for</hi> the <hi>Quakers, to be</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:35672:29"/>
                  <hi>ignorant of the ends of Chriſts Life and Death?</hi> If ſo, what Opinion muſt you needs have of the ignorance of many hundreds among them, that are men of an Orb <hi>much inferior</hi> to <hi>W. P.</hi> Surely they muſt be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant indeed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But pray tell me, how it's poſſible for any <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> (admitting their Notions to be true) to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any thing that is knowable, and neceſſary to be known? ſeeing they ſay, <hi>They have immediate Revelation for the Rule of their Faith and Practice;</hi> and could have known all that is in the Scripture, if it had never been written there, <hi>ONLY by the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Light within them.</hi> But I wonder they ſhould be ſo ignorant, as not to know the Author of the <hi>Quakers Quibbles:</hi> Sure they need not have come ſo often to the Bookſeller to have known, <hi>if the Light within them could have taught them all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they ſhall object and ſay, <hi>It is matter of Fact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, So are many things written in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as, <hi>the names of perſons, the places of their dwellings, things done by them,</hi> &amp;c. and ſome of them <hi>five thouſand years ago:</hi> And ſhall I think they can know things done at ſo great a diſtance, ſeeing they are ſo ignorant as not to know things that are done at preſent?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="principle">
               <head>11. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe eleventh Charge againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> is, <hi>That the Doctrine of Chriſt's Satisfaction, is Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious and Irrational.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. H.</hi>'s Proof is out of <hi>W. P.</hi>'s Sandy Found. <hi>p.</hi> 22. where <hi>W. P.</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>Conſequences</hi> (that is, from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35672:30"/>
this Doctrine) <hi>Irreligious and Irrational;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes one of his Conſequences thus, <hi>O the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Pourtaiture this Doctrine draws of the Infinite Goodneſs! Is this your Retribution? O Injurious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactioniſts!</hi> Thus ſaith <hi>W. P.</hi> But what ſaith <hi>W. L.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>W. L. <hi>Subſtract but the word</hi> Irreligious, <hi>and there have been others, neither Quakers, nor Heathens, nor Illiterate men, that have thought the common under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Chriſt's Satisfaction, as between Creditor and Debtor, to be Irrational; and therefore have Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, how Free-Forgiveneſs, and Full-Satisfaction can ſtand together?</hi> I perceive <hi>T. H.</hi> is no Forger in this neither. But to Reply to <hi>W. L.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As to what he ſaith, <hi>Subſtract but the word</hi> IRRELIGIOUS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, Take away but the word IR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATIONAL too, and then <hi>the Doctrine of Chriſt's Satisfaction is:</hi> But who knows what? But <hi>W. L.</hi> may remember it's put in by <hi>W. P.</hi> and therefore the word <hi>irreligious</hi> is not to be ſubſtracted: <hi>for he ſpeaks by immediate Inſpiration,</hi> as <hi>G. Keith</hi> hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempted to prove in a Publick Diſpute: And <hi>though he could not make it out,</hi> yet they would have People believe it without proof; for <hi>they ſay they witneſs it,</hi> and that may go very far with ſuch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, as <hi>W. L.</hi> repreſents the Quakers to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But if <hi>W. L.</hi> had come to me for advice, when he had been writing on this ſubject, I could have taught him a nearer way to the Wood than he hath gone<hi>:</hi> For if he had but taken away <hi>[Ir]</hi> from both the words, then it had been thus, <hi>That the Doctrine of Chriſt's Satisfaction is Religious and Rational:</hi> And if he could but have perſwaded his intimate Friend
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35672:30"/>
                  <hi>W. P.</hi> and the reſt of the Quakers to have believed it, then I would have perſwaded <hi>T. H.</hi> to have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted the whole Charge, and ſo the Diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and them, as to this particular, ſhould have been ended. But I have cauſe to fear <hi>W. L.</hi> will not undertake that, becauſe he is ſo indifferent about it himſelf, ſaying, <hi>That for the ſake of more neceſſary Truths, he never contends about this.</hi> So that (it ſeems) his ſpeaking to it, is to gratifie <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="principle">
               <head>12. <hi>Pagan Principle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe twelfth and laſt Principle (ſaith <hi>W. L.) T. H.</hi> charges on the Quakers is, <hi>That this body which dies, ſhall not riſe again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The proofs <hi>T. H.</hi> brings to juſtifie himſelf in the truth of this Charge. are as followeth<hi>:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> aſſerted, in the hearing of many witneſſes, <hi>That this body ſhall not riſe again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such a Reſurrection is inconſiſtent with Scripture, Reaſon, and the Belief of all men right in ther wits.</hi> W. Pen. Reaſ. ag. Rail. <hi>p.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſhame let us never make ſo much ſtir againſt the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; for the abſurdity of that is rather outdone than equalled, by this Carnal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi> W. P. ib. <hi>p.</hi> 134.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The change which ſhall be is not of Accidents, but of Bodies.</hi> W. P. ib. <hi>p.</hi> 136. and in <hi>p.</hi> 138. <hi>He calls it a Barbarous Conceit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From our denying the Reſurrection of the Natural and Corruptible Body,</hi> &amp;c. W. P. Counterfeit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>p.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>Now I hope every one will be ſatisfied, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Hicks <hi>is no Forger, Lyer, Slanderer,</hi> &amp;c. as the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35672:31"/>
Lawleſs Quakers have allowed themſelves a liberty (untruly, and without juſt cauſe given) ſo to call him: And I am much perſwaded, the reaſon why they rail and rage thus furiouſly againſt him, is, Becauſe no one of them ſingly, nor the whole Body con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, know how to clear themſelves of thoſe things he hath charged upon them, <hi>without rejecting the chief of their Miniſtry;</hi> whoſe Tongues and Pens have ſo often aſſerted <hi>theſe pernicious Doctrines:</hi> But that I perceive they are not yet willing to do. But let us hear how well <hi>W. L.</hi> can bring up the Reer, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing their denial of that great Fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>The Reſurrection of the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Of all the Articles againſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, none hath made many honeſt, ſerious People more afraid of them, nor the vulgar more rail at them, than this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As for <hi>the vulgars railing,</hi> it concerns not me, they ſhould have forbore divulging ſuch dangerous Notions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But whereas he ſaith, <hi>This Principle of theirs</hi> (in denying the Reſurrection of this Body that dies) <hi>hath made many honeſt, ſerious People more afraid of them, than any other Article they hold:</hi> I think it hath not been without juſt cauſe, from the perniciouſneſs thereof. And I have good Authority to juſtifie me therein; for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If there be no Reſurrection of the dead, then is Chriſt not riſen: And if Chriſt be not riſen, then is our Preaching vain, and your Faith is alſo vain, and ye are yet in your ſins: Then they alſo which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt, are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. And if in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> Theſe are ſome of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35672:31"/>
thoſe evil and dangerous Conſequences, charged by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul upon this very Doctrine</hi> (as maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Quakers) in denying the Reſurrection of this Body from the dead; as you may ſee at large in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But let us hear <hi>W. L.</hi> ſpeak his thoughts about it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaith, <hi>But to tell you freely my thoughts about it, there is leſs cauſe for it upon this account, than any of the former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> I hope thoſe that read this will be fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that there is no more difference between the Quakers and <hi>W. L.</hi> in this Article, than there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Four-pence and a Groat, which (with us in <hi>England)</hi> is the ſame piece of Money. But hath <hi>W. L.</hi> no way left to excuſe his Friends at the laſt gaſp, now their Cauſe is expiring? Yes, yes, don't think you ſhall find him without a ſhift.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>W. L.</hi> Flies to what he ſuppoſes the Charge ſuggeſts; viz. <hi>That there is no Reſurrection; inſomuch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I have heard lewd men ſwear, and curſe them for denying the Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> But here <hi>W. L.</hi> evades the Queſtion, which is ſo plain, that it needs none of his Suggeſtions to darken it. Why don't he anſwer to that? For the Quaker ſaith, <hi>This Body that dies, ſhall not riſe again.</hi> Speak out, and be not afraid to anſwer, now it comes to the point.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſaith W. L. <hi>Doth not their expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all the miſeries of this life, confute the charge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, No: For the Sadducees were men that profeſſed Religion, in oppoſition to the common received Opinion among the Jews, and ſo conſequently were expoſed to ſufferings; and yet
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35672:32"/>
                  <hi>they denied the Reſurrection of this Body, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Angels, which are Spirits,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 8. For it's evident, a <hi>man may give all his goods to the poor, and his body to be burned, and have no love to God,</hi> nor be truly Religious; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 3. And what think you of the <hi>Eſſeans,</hi> a Sect among the Jews, of whom <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports, <hi>That nothwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they denied the Reſurrection of the body, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it is corruptible, and that the matter thereof is not perpetual: Yet could they not be forced to revile their Law-maker, or to eat any forbidden meats, by breaking off the members of their bodies, fiery Torments, and all kind of Tortures which were laid upon them: Nay, in the very midſt of their griefs and pains, they ſcoffed at their Tormentors; and laughing, joyfully yielded up their Souls, as though they hoped to receive them again.</hi> Joſeph. Of the Wars of the Jews, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 616.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas it may be objected. <hi>That they would be more Immoral in their lives, if they expected no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, That the Sadducees were men of ſuch ſtrict lives, that it's reported, they had their name <hi>Sadducees</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tzidek,</hi> which ſignifies, Juſt or Righteous; <hi>and yet they deni'd the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead,</hi> Matth. 22. 23. And for thoſe <hi>Eſſeans</hi> before-mentioned, if he will read <hi>Joſephus,</hi> he may find, <hi>that they were exceeding zealous for the Law, and ſtricter in their lives, than the Quakers are by many degrees:</hi> It's too long to be here inſerted. But if <hi>W. L.</hi> will take the pains to read that Book of <hi>Joſephus</hi> I have mentioned, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. he will find what I ſay to be true. Beſides, it's well known, that there were men among the Heathen, <hi>full of Moral</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35672:32"/>
                  <hi>Vertues, and men of great ſtrictneſs in their lives,</hi> and yet agreed with the Quakers in this, <hi>That this body ſhall not riſe again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> If that be not the Reſurrection intended, what then is it that ſhall riſe from the dead?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> anſwers, <hi>The Apoſtle has given us as good an account of this Doctrine as we may deſire, and to that they refer us. But ſuppoſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they ſhould tell us, This very Body ſhould not riſe, what care</hi> I, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. I am well ſatisfied with the account the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives of the Reſurrection in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. but not at all informed of the Quakers meaning about it, by their referring us thither; becauſe I know <hi>they can Allegorize ſome of the plaineſt Texts in the Bible,</hi> and why may they not be ſuppoſed to do ſo by this?</p>
               <p>2. I cannot poſſibly underſtand, that the Quakers intend the ſame Reſurrection the Apoſtle doth in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. for he tells us, <hi>That the ſame body that is buried</hi> (which he calls ſown) <hi>in corruption, ſhall be raiſed in incorruption.</hi> Which agrees with the ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>The hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth: They that have done good, to the Reſurrection of life; and they that have done evil, to the Reſurrection of damnation,</hi> John 5. 28, 29. As alſo with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel, And many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and everlaſting contempt,</hi> Dan. 12. 2. with many more that might be alledged; all which do <hi>plainly prove the Reſurrection we contend for.</hi> But the Quaker ſaith, <hi>Such a Reſurrection is inconſiſtent with Scripture, Reaſon, and the Belief of all men right in their wits.</hi> Will. Penn. Reaſ. ag. Rail. <hi>p.</hi> 133.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:35672:33"/>
3. But what doth <hi>W. L.</hi> mean when he ſaith, <hi>He is willing to part with this Body for a better? and that he will never be angry with him who promiſeth and aſſures him a pound of Gold, for a pound of Clay?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. If the ſame body ſhall not be raiſed, as the Quakers ſay, then he cannot mean the glorious form of this body, <hi>which ſhall be made incorruptible, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and full of majeſty, like to the glorious Body of Chriſt, with which they ſhall ſhine forth as the Brightneſs of the Sun, in the Kingdom of their Father,</hi> Phil. 3. 21. Matth. 13. 43.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If he means, <hi>That this body which goes into the grave ſhall rot there, and not be raiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united to the ſame ſoul:</hi> But that inſtead thereof, <hi>ſome other matter ſhall be formed into a body, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the ſoul:</hi> This is not to be allowed; for it's highly rational, That if any body be raiſed and re-united to the ſoul, it ſhould be the ſame body (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture declares, <hi>That the end of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Man is, that he might receive a reward according to the deeds done in the body,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 10. and, <hi>that the Righteous ſhall go into life Eternal,</hi> Matth. 25. <hi>ult.)</hi> Seeing it was the ſame body in which theſe good deeds were done, why ſhould not the ſame body receive the Reward together with the ſame ſoul? why muſt there be a new, another body to enjoy it, made of they know not what?</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this be ſo, Then whether it be not moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to imagine <hi>(ſeeing ſome men ſhall be damned)</hi> that one body ſhould commit the ſin, and another body, that never ſinned, <hi>ſhould ſuffer Eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Hell,</hi> for thoſe ſins <hi>another committed?</hi> This is <hi>to condemn the innocent, and acquit the guilty:</hi> Both
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35672:33"/>
which <hi>are an Abomination to the Lord:</hi> And the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers can no ways avoid this Abſurdity, unleſs they will ſay, <hi>That no man ſhall be damned:</hi> Which I take to be the neceſſary Conſequence of their affirming, <hi>The Soul to be a part of God's Being;</hi> and their deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The Reſurrection of the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If ſo, then all that <hi>W. L.</hi> hath done, is but Quibling; for all the Reſurrection he and they muſt be underſtood to intend, <hi>is only within men</hi> while they are in this World. And in truth, their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about the Reſurrection (as worded by ſome of their noted Teachers) is this:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Reſurrection of the unjuſt, is ſins riſing in man, and getting above the Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Eternal Judgment, is the Lights condemning and reproving for ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>And as any one comes to hearken to the Teaching thereof, the Light comes to riſe up in him: Which</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is the Reſurrection of the juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now from hence they infer, <hi>That they are in the Reſurrection, and paſt the Eternal Judgment, even in this life;</hi> and that it is <hi>not they themſelves,</hi> that ſhall riſe, <hi>but the Light within them: Which Light</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is ſufficient to lead them into all Truth, cleanſe them from all ſin, and will Eternally ſave them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that <hi>W. L.</hi> hath diſcharged <hi>T. H.</hi> of <hi>Forgery</hi> in all theſe <hi>Twelve Pagan Principles of the Quakers.</hi> But how the Quakers can clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of <hi>Lies and Forgery,</hi> would do well to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; ſeeing they tell <hi>T. H.</hi> that he hath <hi>belyed</hi> them, when he hath not charged them with any thing in all theſe particulars, but what is <hi>truly charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon them:</hi> As appears by this brief Account, and <hi>W. L.</hi>'s <hi>Confeſſion</hi> under each Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:35672:34"/>
But ſaith <hi>Geo. Whitehead, I hope you have conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that moderate Account which your Friend and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> W. L. <hi>hath given in his Book, entituled,</hi> The Twelve Pagan Principles or Opinions, &amp;c. <hi>and what a ſerious Check it containeth to</hi> Thomas Hicks, <hi>for his immoderation, and unfair dealing.</hi> G. W. in <hi>The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Plainneſs detecting Fallacy,</hi> p. 88. Now that there is no reaſon to account him <hi>a Baptiſt,</hi> as <hi>G. W.</hi> doth in theſe words, becauſe they are the perſons to whom he writes, I will here inſert a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> given under the hands of two of the <hi>eminenteſt Baptiſts</hi> in thoſe parts, where he hath had his abode for above ſeven years paſt; that in all that ſpace of time, he hath not been a Member with them, nor any of the Churches to whom they belong, much leſs <hi>a Sober Baptiſt-Preacher,</hi> as the Quakers had the confidence to call him in the Title-page of their Book, touching the <hi>Barbican-Meeting, Octob.</hi> 9. 1674.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="certification">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THis is to certifie, That</hi> WILLIAM LUDDINGTON <hi>hath never been in Communion with the Congregations in the Country to whom we belong, either in</hi> Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamſhire, <hi>or the County of</hi> Hertford <hi>(which are the places in which he hath lived for above ſeven years laſt paſt) ſo as to partake with us in that</hi> Holy Ordinance of the Lord's Supper.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Witneſs our hands, Tho. Monck. Tho. Heyward.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1. 1674.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:35672:34"/>
I have two things to tell the World, and I have done.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An Account of ſome <hi>Slanders,</hi> and <hi>Abuſes</hi> of the <hi>Quakers</hi> caſt upon me, for my <hi>oppoſing their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Open and manifeſt <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of ſome <hi>Eminent in the Quakers Miniſtry,</hi> concerning the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and, <hi>His dying for our ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As touching the firſt of theſe: I being at the <hi>Bull and Mouth,</hi> May 8. 1674. and demanding of them to prove that Great Principle of theirs, which <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> was ſo baffled about in his Diſpute with Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> in the Market-place at <hi>Croyden</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> April 24. 1674. before hundreds of people. The Queſtion was this:</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Whether every man that comes into the World, is enlightned with the Light of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They did then <hi>affirm it:</hi> But when they ſaw they could not prove it, I was ſo <hi>pulled, ſtruck, and abuſed,</hi> that I was not able to keep my ſtanding, and attend the Diſcourſe: They alſo made ſuch a Bawling on purpoſe to prevent my being heard, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to hear what was ſaid: And at laſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any further Diſcourſe, one of them concludes the Meeting in prayer.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman that was a ſtranger being preſent, and obſerving the violence they offered to my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, came up into the Gallery where I was, and ſaid, <hi>Sir, I perceive, that if a man comes to diſpute with theſe men, he had need to take a Guard with him to ſecure his perſon.</hi> And as we went out, one crys out, <hi>Children of</hi> Babylon, <hi>Brats of</hi> Babylon; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, <hi>Thou art a Blaſphemer,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:35672:35"/>
I being there again, <hi>May</hi> 15. 1674. to hear whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had any thing further to ſay to that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion before-mentioned: And when their Friend in the Miniſtry had done, and I began to ſpeak to the Queſtion, one that is called a Friend in their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, whoſe name is <hi>Samuel Thornton,</hi> thruſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and the poſt where I ſtood, and another Quaker cruſhed me up on the other ſide; the Rail of the Gallery was before me, and a crowd of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers at my back thronging upon me, and my leg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Baniſters, which were turned with knobs; he pitched his knee againſt mine, and his elbow againſt my breaſt, leaning upon me with his weight; and I having no liberty to give way, my breath was in danger of being forced out of my body, and my ſhirt wet with ſweat, as if it had been dipt in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And not being able to endure it, upon giving notice to the people, there came up ſome very luſty men, that were not Quakers, and relieved me.</p>
               <p>After this, when <hi>Sam. Thornton</hi> ſaw he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of his purpoſe he railed upon me, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thou art a Thief, a Lyer, a Murderer, a Devil, Thy name is</hi> Cain; and then cried out with a loud voice, <hi>Cain, Cain, Cain, Cain, Cain,</hi> juſt like a man bereft of his Reaſon. One ſaid, <hi>I was a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard;</hi> another <hi>Thou art drunk every day in the week.</hi> I not knowing what opinion ſome might have of me, that did not know my Converſation, asked what they meant by ſaying, I was a Drunkard? One of them anſwered, <hi>Thou art drunk with words, beſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ignorance,</hi> &amp;c. Now if theſe men can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves a liberty thus to rail againſt one, at ſo deſperate a rate, againſt whom they can prove none of thoſe things whereof they accuſe him, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35672:35"/>
when they have done, excuſe it by ſaying, <hi>We meant Allegorically:</hi> Who then can have his Reputation ſecured from theſe mens virulent and reproachful Tongues?</p>
               <p>I being at the ſame Meeting place ſome time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hearing ſuch expreſſions about Chriſt, which had a tendency to beguile the ignorant<hi>:</hi> When he that was ſpeaking had done, I offered to diſcourſe ſoberly with them about it; which they refuſed. Whereupon I told the People, that the Quakers held theſe Opinions; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt is not a diſtinct Perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That Chriſt, in reſpect of himſelf, never died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Blood of Chriſt, ſhed upon the Croſs, without the gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>is of no more value in point of Juſtification, than the blood of another man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That the Imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which he fulfilled for us in his own Perſon, wholly without us, is a Doctrine of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Quakers <hi>refuſing to anſwer,</hi> notwithſtanding I offered to make good each of theſe particulars them; I told the People, that I hoped they would believe what I had charged upon them; <hi>i. e. That they were afraid to bring their Doctrines to be tried by the Light of the Holy Scriptures;</hi> like thoſe ſpoken of by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> whom he calls by the name of <hi>Lucifugae Scripturarum, Men that fly from the Light of the Scripture, as the Bats do into their holes, when the Sun appears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon <hi>Francis Campfield</hi> ſtood up and ſaid, <hi>Thou art my Neighbour, and I know thee:</hi> And then made a ſpeech to the people, telling them, <hi>He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired they would take no notice of what I ſaid, for I</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:35672:36"/>
                  <hi>was ſomewhat diſtempered in my head.</hi> Giving a ſtrong Indication to the people, <hi>That I was a diſtracted man,</hi> and ſo <hi>not fit to ue diſcourſed with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I told him, I hoped the people would not believe what he had ſaid; but in caſe they ſhould, if the <hi>Quakers</hi> would be pleaſed to appoint time and place, I would procure a man that ſhould make good all that I had charged upon them, whom they ſhould acknowledg to be in his right wits: <hi>But they refuſed to accept of that offer alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I being at the <hi>Barbican-Meeting, Octob.</hi> 9. 1674. fell into ſome Diſcourſe with a <hi>Quaker:</hi> Another that ſtood by, ſeeing his Friend at a loſs, pulled him by the arm, ſaying, <hi>That I was a diſtracted man,</hi> or to that effect. The <hi>Quaker</hi> I was talking with, cried out, <hi>Alas for him, is this he!</hi> I told him he was miſtaken, for (I thank the Lord) I am not in that condition. He preſently replied, <hi>I was ſo, for</hi> Francis Campfield <hi>had declared me ſo to be in the Meeting at the</hi> Bull and Mouth. By this the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may ſee, what ſubtil Artifices theſe men make uſe of to evade the force of an Argument. What did all this ſignifie to the matter in debate? was it not a meer ſhift?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Open and manifeſt <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of ſome <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in the Quakers Miniſtry,</hi> concerning the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and, <hi>His dying for our ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I and many others, being preſent at Mr. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> a Dyer in <hi>Oldſtreet,</hi> we heard <hi>Joſiah Cole</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, <hi>That that Man which was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and ſuffered at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>without the gate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is not the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World.</hi> And he would needs undertake the proof it: And having agreed beforehand, that the Scripture ſhould be the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35672:36"/>
Rule to try that preſent Controverſie by (though he would not own it as the Rule of Faith) he attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prove it as followeth:</p>
               <p>J. C. <hi>It is written</hi> Iſa. 45. 21, 22. I am God, and there is none elſe, a juſt God and a Saviour, there is none beſides me: <hi>From whence he drew this inference; If God be the Saviour, and there is none beſides him, then that Man is not the Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was replied, That Chriſt was God as well as man; and therefore his Argument was inſufficient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> It was asked <hi>J. C.</hi> Whether the Light or Spirit in that Man, was not the Chriſt? And he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Yea, it is ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> His Reſpondent replied, A Spirit hath no fleſh to be broken, nor blood to be ſhed; therefore if his Notion were true, Chriſt never died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſaih Cole</hi> did affirm, (with a great deal of ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeriouſneſs) <hi>That the true Chriſt, in reſpect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, never died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Friend of mine being preſent, one Mr. <hi>J. D.</hi> brake forth into Admiration, ſaying, <hi>He ſaith Chriſt never ſuffered.</hi> There being about eight of the chief <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>London</hi> preſent, one of them ſaid, <hi>Thou lieſt, he did not ſay Chriſt never ſuffered (for he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in thee and others) but he ſaid, Chriſt never dyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I met with <hi>Joſiah Cole</hi> twice afterwards, and both times diſcourſed with him about that point; and he was very poſitive and peremptory in it, aſſerting with the greateſt confidence imaginable, <hi>That Chriſt never died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At another time, being at <hi>Edw. Mans</hi> the Hoſier, I and divers others then preſent, heard <hi>Patrick Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingſtone</hi> (another owned in the Miniſtry) affirm,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35672:37"/>
                  <hi>That Chriſt, in reſpect of himſelf, never died, neither could he, becauſe he was only God: There was indeed a holy Body, which he (i. e.</hi> The Light in him) <hi>took up, acted in for a time, and laid down again: But that Body was no part of the Chriſt, but only a holy Body in which he was.</hi> I then brought that Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 39. to prove he had a Body, as well after, as before his Reſurrection; <hi>Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I my ſelf, handle me and ſee, for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones, as you ſee me have.</hi> But it ſeems this very ſaying of our Saviour was ſo diſtaſteful to them, that about ten of the <hi>Quakers</hi> cried out together, <hi>Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy, his Chriſt is a Chriſt of fleſh and bones; Blaſphemy:</hi> And that without any Provocation thereunto; for I made no Comment upon the words. And at the ſame time <hi>Charles Harris,</hi> another Eminent in the Miniſtry, being asked, Whether that holy Ordinance of the Lord's Supper was now to be practiſed? ſaid, <hi>It's written,</hi> If any man hear my voice, and open the door, I will come in and ſup with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rev. 3. 20. <hi>This is the Supper of the Lord, we witneſs it:</hi> And about the Reſurrection and Judgment to come he ſaid, <hi>I ſpeak this from the Eternal God, That the Reſurrection is come, the Judgment is come, and I witneſs it.</hi> And this very well agrees with <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi>'s words, in his Book of <hi>Queſtions about Chriſt,</hi> p. 14. <hi>Now Friends, if you would know or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve aright, you muſt believe in him who was with the Father before the World was, who was the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the Jeſus, the Chriſt, from Everlaſting. This we firmly believe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yea, it is he to whom the name Jeſus and Chriſt did of right belong, before he took up the Body: For that which he took upon him, was</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:35672:37"/>
                  <hi>our garment, even the fleſh and blood of our Nature, which is of an earthly and periſhing Nature: But he is of an Eternal Nature, and his fleſh, blood, and bones are of his Nature,</hi> viz. Eternal: <hi>For that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems, that which is Jeſus the Saviour, came down from Heaven,</hi> page 20. que. 7. que. 8.</p>
               <p>Reader, Not knowing how ſhort my time may be, I thought good to leave this to Poſterity, leſt I ſhould not have ſuch another opportunity: And will conclude with that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye therefore beloved, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leſt ye alſo being led away with the errour of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs: But grow in grace, and the knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; to him be glory, both now and for ever, Amen,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:35672:38"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>SInce the finiſhing theſe Papers in anſwer to <hi>W. L.</hi> I have been earneſtly importuned to write a few lines touching that great Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>about the Lord Chriſt,</hi> as it relates to the <hi>Quakers Opinion:</hi> And to ſhew <hi>who it is to whom the name</hi> Chriſt <hi>doth properly belong.</hi> And although I think my ſelf a Child in the knowledg of ſuch Divine and Metaphyſical Truths, compared with thoſe Worthies of our Age, whoſe parts and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Acquirements may more amply fit them for ſuch a Work: Yet ſeeing they have hitherto omitted it, I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to it; hoping it may be an occaſion to ſet ſome abler Pen on work to diſcourſe more accurately upon this ſubject: And by poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what I have more briefly laid down, they may make the Truth appear more perſpicuouſly in its own Brightneſs and Splendor. And I will give you the Queſtion, as it is laid down by Mr. <hi>PENN</hi> in the <hi>Barbican-Meeting,</hi> and ſince printed, and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by ſome of the chief Quakers in</hi> London, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35672:38"/>
               <hi>W. Mead, J. Oſgood, W. Shewen, E. Man, S. Newton, J. Claypool, W. Welch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. P.</hi>'s Queſtion is this, <hi>Was he the Chriſt of God before he was manifeſted in the fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, He was never called the Chriſt of God before, but with reſpect to what he was to be, when, and after he was manifeſted in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>To make this good, I ſhall uſe this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To explain what is meant by the word <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſhew that it is <hi>taken Relatively,</hi> is a <hi>name of Office,</hi> and as ſuch <hi>applied to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That this name cannot be <hi>properly and really</hi> applied to the Divine Nature, <hi>taken Abſtractively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That it doth <hi>properly and really belong</hi> to that <hi>Sacred</hi> Perſon, who was <hi>Conceived</hi> by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Born</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and called by the name of <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To explain what is meant by the word <hi>Chriſt:</hi> It is a Derivative from the Hebrew and Greek, the two Original Languages in which the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were written. The word in the Hebrew is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Maſhiach;</hi> in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Chriſtos;</hi> in the Latin <hi>Chriſtus:</hi> All which ſignifie in Engliſh, <hi>Anointed:</hi> Being derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ungo:</hi> All ſignifying to <hi>Anoint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is <hi>taken Relatively,</hi> and is a <hi>name of Office,</hi> &amp;c. appears from the frequent uſe thereof in the Old-Teſtament, and applied to <hi>Prieſts, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> who were <hi>anointed</hi> with Oyl when they entred upon their Offices; and therefore were called, <hi>The Lord's Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:35672:39"/>
1. To Prieſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40. 13, 14, 15. <hi>And thou ſhalt put upon</hi> Aaron <hi>the holy Garments, and anoint him, and ſanctifie him, that he may miniſter unto me in the Prieſts Office. And thou ſhalt bring his ſons, and clothe them with coats; and thou ſhalt anoint them, as thou didſt anoint their Father, that they may mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter unto me in the Prieſts Office:</hi> And this was to be obſerved as a Rule throughout all their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Touching the other two Offices of <hi>Prophet</hi> and <hi>King;</hi> we find the ſame method uſed in both, and that <hi>by the Command of God himſelf</hi> to the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 Kin. 19. 15, 16. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto him, Go—Anoint</hi> Hazael <hi>to be King over</hi> Syria. <hi>And</hi> Jehu <hi>the ſon of</hi> Nimſhi <hi>ſhalt thou anoint to be King over</hi> Iſrael. <hi>And</hi> Eliſha <hi>the ſon of</hi> Shaphat <hi>of</hi> Abel-Meh-lah <hi>ſhalt thou anoint to be Prophet in thy room.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that the name <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo <hi>applied to him,</hi> viz. <hi>Relatively,</hi> and as a <hi>name of Office,</hi> I ſhall prove, by ſhewing you:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is called, a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he was anointed by God the Father, when he entred upon his Offices.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he is called a <hi>Prieſt:</hi> Theſe Scriptures following do ſufficiently evince. <hi>But Chriſt being come an High-Prieſt of good things to come,</hi> Heb. 9. 11. <hi>The High-Prieſt of our Profeſſion Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Heb. 3. 1. <hi>This man becauſe he continueth ever, hath an unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prieſthood,</hi> Heb. 7. 24. <hi>Seeing then that we have a great High-Prieſt, that is paſſed into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Jeſus the Son of God, let us hold faſt our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. For we have not an High-Prieſt which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:35672:39"/>
               <hi>was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without ſin,</hi> Heb. 4. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That he is called a <hi>Prophet: Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was a Prophet, mighty in deed and word before God, and all the people,</hi> Luke 24. 19. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, that every Soul which will not hear that Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people,</hi> Acts 3. 23.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That he is called a <hi>King: Pilate</hi> called Jeſus, and ſaid unto him, <hi>Art thou the King of the Jews? Jeſus anſwered, My Kingdom is not of this World. Pilate</hi> therefore ſaid unto him, <hi>Art thou a King then?</hi> Jeſus anſwered, <hi>Thou ſayeſt that I am a King: To this end was I born, and for this cauſe came I into the World,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 18. 33. &amp; 36, 37. Nathaneel <hi>anſwered and ſaith unto him, Rabbi, thou art the Son of God, thou art the King of Iſrael,</hi> John 1. 49. <hi>Who is the bleſſed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and the Lord of Lords,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 15. <hi>And he hath on his Veſture, and on his Thigh, a name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> KING OF KINGS AND LORD OF LORDS, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. 16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Chriſt was <hi>Anointed</hi> by God the Father, when he entred upon his Offices, <hi>with the holy Spirit:</hi> As the <hi>Prieſts, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, were <hi>anointed with Oyl,</hi> when they entred upon <hi>Theirs;</hi> ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 16, 17. <hi>And Jeſus when he was baptized, went up ſtraightway out of the water: And lo, the Heavens were opened unto him, and he ſaw the Spirit of God deſcending like a Dove, and lighting upon him: And lo, a voice from Heaven, ſaying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Heb. 1. 9. <hi>Therefore God, even thy God hath Anointed thee with the Oyl of Gladneſs above thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35672:40"/>
Luke 4. 17, 18, 21. <hi>And there was delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the Book of</hi> Eſaias<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>the Prophet; and when he had opened the Book, he found the place where it is written, The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c. And applied this to his own Perſon, as being then fulfilled, <hi>Then he began to ſay unto them, This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your ears.</hi> The word which God ſent unto the Children of Iſrael was this, That <hi>God had Anointed Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth <hi>with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Power, who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppreſſed of the Devil; for God was with him,</hi> Acts 10. 38. Now by this we may ſee, that as his Name is, ſo is the Perſon to whom it is given; for he <hi>being Anointed with the Holy Spirit above his fellows,</hi> he is <hi>properly and truly</hi> the Lord's Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That this Name cannot be <hi>properly and really</hi> applied to the Divine Nature, <hi>taken Abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively:</hi> And my Reaſon for it is this, Becauſe ſome of thoſe things which were done by <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> could not have been performed by <hi>the Divine Nature</hi> in the ſenſe before defined.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe if they could, there had then been no need for him to have been a man, made of a woman, to be made fleſh and dwell among men, to have been expoſed to all thoſe ſufferings and ſorrows which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel him in the days of his fleſh, while he was upon the earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt died for our ſins according to the Scripture,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 3. But the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> taken Abſtractively <hi>cannot die:</hi> For beſides this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Nature of the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence cannot poſſibly admit of it, and it's horrid Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy to aſſert it: So on the contrary, it is poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35672:40"/>
affirmed, <hi>That God lives for ever.</hi> If I lift up my hand to Heaven, and ſay, <hi>I live for ever,</hi> Deut. 32. 40. yea, he ſwears by himſelf, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 49. 18. <hi>The name of the Lord, the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God,</hi> Gen. 21. 33. For thus ſaith the High and Loſty One <hi>that inhabiteth Eternity,</hi> Iſa. 57. 15. <hi>whoſe goings forth have been from of old, from everlaſting,</hi> Micah. 5. 2. <hi>Lord thou haſt been our dwelling-place in all Generations. Before the Mountains were brought forth, or ever thou hadſt formed the Earth, and the World, even from everlaſting to everlaſting, thou art God,</hi> Pſal. 90. 1, 2. And God ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, I AM that I AM, Thus ſhalt thou ſay unto the Children of Iſrael, I AM hath ſent me unto you: This is my name for ever; And this is my Memorial unto all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations,</hi> Exod. 3. 14, 15. The <hi>Certainty, Perpetuity,</hi> and <hi>Eternity</hi> of <hi>Gods Being,</hi> aſſures Believers of the <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> of all his <hi>Promiſes;</hi> ſeeing they know he is <hi>faithful,</hi> and <hi>cannot lie,</hi> nor <hi>ceaſe to be:</hi> For if he could <hi>do either,</hi> it would take away all the Foundation of our Faith and Hope in God, his Word and Promiſes.</p>
            <p>But there are ſome Objections urged by the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in print againſt this Truth, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. P.</hi> Askes this Queſtion, <hi>Was he the Chriſt of God before he was manifeſted in the fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> anſwers, He was the Son of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> W. P. <hi>But was he the Lords Chriſt?</hi> And turns this Anſwer to it himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> W. P. ſaith, <hi>I will prove him to have been the Lords Chriſt, as well before as after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>From the Apoſtle Paul's words to the</hi> Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>That Rock was Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:35672:41"/>
2. <hi>Next, from</hi> Jude, <hi>where ſome Greek Copies have it thus, That Jeſus brought the people of Iſrael out of Egypt.</hi> See <hi>The Quakers Account of the Barbican-Meeting, p.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I will anſwer to the laſt firſt, If <hi>W. P.</hi> have ſeen any ſuch Greek Copies, he ſhould have cited them, and told us what they are: Till which time, I ſhall account it as the effect of paſſion ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in the defence of a bad cauſe. But ſurely <hi>W. P.</hi> forgot himſelf to bring this Allegation; for if this be brought to prove any thing, it is, <hi>That he as Jeſus was before he was manifeſted in the fleſh:</hi> Which name was never given to him till he came in the fleſh; <hi>And ſhe ſhall bring forth a Son, and thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus. And ſhe brought forth her firſt-born Son, and he called his name Jeſus,</hi> Matth. 1. 21, 25. Beſides, our Engliſh Tranſlation doth very well agree with the Greek; for in <hi>Jude,</hi> v. 5. which is the place he refers to, the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in our Tranſlation, Lord; which is the expreſs ſignification of the word, and ſo rendred in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of places in the New-Teſtament. And this can be brought by <hi>W. P.</hi> for no better purpoſe than to undervalue the Scripture, by quarrelling with the Tranſlation, though there be no cauſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As for thoſe words in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>That Rock was Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, It's meant, <hi>not really,</hi> but <hi>figuratively;</hi> as appears by the precedent words, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>And did all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpiritual drink: for they drank of the ſpiritual Rock that followed them; and that Rock was Chriſt.</hi> For it's evident;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:35672:41"/>
1. That there was a <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>True Rock,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmote with his Rod, and out of which the water guſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the people of Iſrael <hi>drunk of this Water</hi> to quench their thirſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this was <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>True Water;</hi> becauſe their <hi>Cattel alſo</hi> drank thereof, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20. 11. <hi>He ſmote the Rock twice, and the Water came out abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, and the Congregation drank, and their Beaſts alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Water</hi> which came out of that <hi>Rock</hi> became <hi>Rivers,</hi> and <hi>followed</hi> them in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>He brought ſtreams alſo out of the Rock, and cauſed waters to run down like Rivers,</hi> Pſal. 78. 16. <hi>Behold he ſmote the Rock, that the waters guſhed out, and the ſtreams overflowed,</hi> ver. 20. <hi>And they thirſted not when he led them through the Deſerts:</hi> And in the next words you have an Account how they were ſupplied in this their journey through the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts; <hi>He cauſed the waters to flow out of the Rock for them: He clave the Rock alſo, and the water guſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out,</hi> Iſa. 48. 21. <hi>He opened the Rock, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters guſhed out, they ran in the dry places like a River, Pſal.</hi> 105. 41. And therefore it's ſaid, <hi>The Rock fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them;</hi> Which by a <hi>Metonymie</hi> is meant the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that came out of the <hi>Rock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It's called, <hi>A ſpiritual Rock,</hi> becauſe it was <hi>Typical of Chriſt;</hi> and that the Believers among them did as truly partake of Chriſt <hi>by Faith ſpiritually,</hi> as <hi>They,</hi> the reſt of <hi>the Multitude,</hi> and <hi>their Cattel,</hi> did drink of the water of the Rock <hi>literally.</hi> And in the ſame ſenſe that the <hi>MANNA</hi> is called <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Meat,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>They did all eat the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35672:42"/>
               <hi>Meat;</hi> ſo is the <hi>water of the Rock,</hi> called <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Drink. They did all drink the ſame ſpiritual Drink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we may not conclude from hence, <hi>That that Rock was really Chriſt;</hi> or that he was called Chriſt, with reſpect to what he was <hi>before he was manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh:</hi> But on the contrary, it's to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>the Faith they had in the promiſed Meſſias that was to come,</hi> whereof that <hi>Rock</hi> was a <hi>Type.</hi> So that this manner of ſpeaking agrees with that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Saviour, Abraham <hi>rejoyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad,</hi> John 8. 56. which was not really by <hi>an Ocular view of his Perſon,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>then preſent,</hi> but by the <hi>Faith</hi> he had <hi>in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> that he ſhould be revealed <hi>in the fulneſs of Time:</hi> for it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the reſt of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 13. <hi>Theſe all died in Faith, not having received the Promiſes; but having ſeen them afar off, and were perſwaded of them:</hi> The principal of which was, <hi>The promiſe of the Meſſias that was to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be objected, <hi>That in</hi> Pſal. 2. 2. <hi>in the Latin Bible, tranſlated by</hi> Beza, <hi>it is ſaid,</hi> Et contra Chriſtum ejus; And againſt his Chriſt. <hi>And the like in</hi> Dan. 9. <hi>Therefore he is called Chriſt, before he was manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. It's true, he is called <hi>Chriſt, Meſſiah,</hi> and <hi>the Anointed</hi> in thoſe places: And if we will believe a very Learned Author of our time, he ſaith, <q>The name of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is but twice or thrice at moſt, uſed in the Old-Teſtament, directly and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to denote the promiſed Seed; namely, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 25, 26. whereunto <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 2. may be added.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35672:42"/>
                  <hi>J. Owen</hi> D. D. <hi>Exercit.</hi> 9. on the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> p. 95.</q> So that theſe are <hi>all the places</hi> in the Old-Teſtament <hi>wherein he is ſo called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is alſo true, That the word in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Maſhiach,</hi> both in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. which ſignifies, <hi>Anointed,</hi> and is applied to <hi>our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So that I grant all that is in the Objection.</p>
            <p>But it doth not thence follow, That becauſe he is is called ſo before, that it doth not reſpect what he was to be, when, and after he was manifeſted in the fleſh; but the contrary is manifeſt by the ſcope of thoſe Texts, to any conſidering perſon: For in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. it is ſaid, <hi>The Kings of the Earth have ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Rulers take counſel together, againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt:</hi> Now in <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. upon the Threatnings they had from the Rulers, Chief Prieſts and Elders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe very words upon that occaſion; <hi>Who by the mouth of thy ſervant</hi> David <hi>haſt ſaid, The Kings of the Earth ſtood up, and the Rulers were gathered together, againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt; for of a truth, againſt thy Holy Child Jeſus whom thou haſt Anointed, both</hi> Herod <hi>and</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>with the Gentiles, and the People of Iſrael were gathered together, for to do whatſoever thy hand and thy counſel determined before to be done. And, now Lord, behold their Threatnings, and grant unto thy ſervants, that with all boldneſs they may ſpeak thy Word: By ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth thy hand to heal, and that ſigns and wonders may be done by the Name of thy Holy Child Jeſus.</hi> So that you may ſee, that this oppoſition <hi>in the Kings againſt Chriſt,</hi> was upon the account of his
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35672:43"/>
being <hi>manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> and introducing <hi>a new Doctrine and Religion in the World;</hi> which ſet them in a rage <hi>againſt him and his Diſciples.</hi> And this is the plain meaning of this Text.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. it's ſaid, <hi>Know therefore and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, That from the going forth of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to reſtore and to build Jeruſalem, unto the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah the Prince, ſhall be ſeven weeks: And after three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and two weeks, ſhall Meſſiah be cut off, but not for himſelf: And the People of the Prince that ſhall come, ſhall deſtroy the City, and the Sanctuary, and the end thereof ſhall be with a flood, and unto the end of the War, deſolations are determined.</hi> All theſe things <hi>were yet to come</hi> when this was ſpoken, and <hi>not fulfilled</hi> till the <hi>days of his fleſh:</hi> For here is <hi>his own death</hi> expreſly propheſied of, the <hi>deſtruction of Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Deſolation of</hi> that <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it is objected by <hi>Geo. Keith: But I prove, that he was Jeſus Chriſt before he took fleſh,</hi> Eph. 3. 9. <hi>Who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. I grant, <hi>That God did Create all things by Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> But it was, <hi>as he was God,</hi> and <hi>not as he is a man in the fleſh:</hi> And yet as ſuch, he was <hi>the Chriſt of God,</hi> being <hi>Anointed with the Spirit,</hi> as is ſhewed above.</p>
            <p>2. If this be true that <hi>G. K.</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he was both Anointed, and a Saviour before the World was:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. I would then know:</p>
            <p n="1">1. How he came to be in a capacity to receive that <hi>Anointing,</hi> ſeeing <hi>then</hi> he was <hi>only God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Who <hi>Anointed him?</hi> ſeeing you ſay, <hi>There is no diſtinction of Perſons in the Divine Eſſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:35672:43"/>
3. What <hi>ſinners</hi> were there for him to <hi>ſave,</hi> before <hi>any thing was created?</hi> For he is called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he came to ſave his People from their ſins,</hi> Matth. 1. 21.</p>
            <p>But I take this to be the genuine ſenſe of that Text, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 9. That he being then beſt known by the names of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and known to be <hi>a real and true Man,</hi> the Apoſtle would let them know, that he was alſo <hi>truly God;</hi> ſeeing he did <hi>Create all things:</hi> But was ſo far from being Jeſus Chriſt <hi>then,</hi> that he ſaith, <hi>the knowledg</hi> of his <hi>Revelation</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> was ſo great a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>known,</hi> that from the beginning of the World it hath been <hi>hid in God,</hi> and was now revealed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Eternal purpoſe of God,</hi> which he <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus our Lord:</hi> Which in <hi>other Ages</hi> was not <hi>made known</hi> to the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> as it is <hi>now</hi> revealed unto his <hi>holy Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> by the <hi>Spirit;</hi> as you may ſee at large in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>So that he intends not by theſe words, that he was <hi>then</hi> the <hi>Saviour Anointed,</hi> any more than the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth intend he was <hi>really ſlain</hi> from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World; and yet it is ſaid ſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 8. by him <hi>who calls things</hi> that <hi>are not,</hi> as though <hi>they were,</hi> becauſe he hath <hi>decreed it,</hi> and <hi>his Decrees</hi> ſhall be <hi>accompliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the ſame Rule <hi>G. K.</hi> might as well have ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>Born, Dead,</hi> and <hi>Buried</hi> in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s <hi>time;</hi> becauſe it's ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9 6. <hi>Vnto us a Child is Born;</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 53. 11. he hath poured out his Soul <hi>unto Death; verſ.</hi> 9. and <hi>he made his Grave</hi> with the wicked, and with the rich <hi>in his death.</hi> All this being ſpoken in the <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terperfect</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:35672:44"/>
tenſe. But if <hi>the Light within them</hi> can <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret</hi> Scripture <hi>no better,</hi> I will not <hi>conſult</hi> it as my <hi>Oracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time I hope, not only <hi>theſe</hi> Objections are removed, but <hi>all others</hi> of the <hi>like import,</hi> may <hi>eaſily</hi> be <hi>anſwered</hi> by <hi>theſe</hi> Diſtinctions; which I ſhould have <hi>particularly</hi> ſpoken to, only the <hi>Paper allotted me</hi> will not <hi>permit</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That it doth properly and really belong to that ſacred Perſon, who was Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, Born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and called by the name of Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth.</p>
            <p>To make this good, I ſhall uſe this method:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew you <hi>what this Sacred Perſon is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>that very Perſon</hi> who is called <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> is alſo called <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Name <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth <hi>properly and really</hi> belong to <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhew you <hi>what this Sacred Perſon is:</hi> I do affirm, That he is both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and that the <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of his <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> doth <hi>ſo conſtitute</hi> this <hi>Sacred Perſon,</hi> that <hi>both</hi> of them, as <hi>united,</hi> are the <hi>Chriſt of God:</hi> And that when the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>acts</hi> done by <hi>him</hi> as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they are to be underſtood as <hi>performed</hi> by that <hi>Perſon</hi> ſo conſidered.</p>
            <p>To make this good, I ſhall prove three things<hi>:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That this Sacred Perſon <hi>is God.</hi> And becauſe the Quakers own him whom they call Chriſt to be <hi>God,</hi> I ſhall only cite that known place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>Whoſe are the Fathers, and of whom, as concerning the fleſh, Chriſt came; who is over all, God bleſſed for ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:35672:44"/>
2. That he is alſo <hi>truly Man.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>For there is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the MAN Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Acts 2. 22, 23. <hi>Ye men of Iſrael, hear theſe words, Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>a MAN approved among you, by Miracles, Wonders, and Signs which God did by him in the midſt of you, as ye your ſelves alſo know: Him ye have taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and ſlain.</hi> But if he had not been <hi>truly Man,</hi> he could not have been <hi>put to death</hi> by the <hi>hands of men;</hi> for, as I have proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> for the <hi>Deity</hi> to become <hi>Mortal.</hi> But I ſhall ſay no more to this here, having proved Chriſt to be a <hi>real and true Man,</hi> p. 18, 19. to which I refer you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That thoſe <hi>acts</hi> done by him <hi>as Chriſt,</hi> are to be underſtood as <hi>performed</hi> by that <hi>Perſon,</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>as God and Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of this, conſider;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>ſome acts</hi> done <hi>by him,</hi> cannot be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>as he is God,</hi> taken <hi>Abſtractively;</hi> for <hi>as ſuch,</hi> he cannot <hi>be made fleſh,</hi> he cannot <hi>die,</hi> and be made <hi>a Sacrifice for ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>ſome</hi> acts <hi>alſo</hi> are done by <hi>him,</hi> which cannot be <hi>performed</hi> by his <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> taken <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractively;</hi> for <hi>as ſuch,</hi> he cannot <hi>know all things,</hi> he cannot be <hi>every-where preſent,</hi> neither could he have given <hi>plenary Satisfaction</hi> to the <hi>Juſtice of God</hi> for the <hi>ſins of men,</hi> had not his <hi>Humanity</hi> been <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported</hi> by his <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and <hi>united</hi> to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet that <hi>theſe things</hi> are <hi>aſcribed</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> as he is a <hi>Perſon</hi> conſiſting both of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature:</hi> And that this <hi>is ſo,</hi> I will give you ſome few inſtances;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:35672:45"/>
1. That in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28. <hi>Feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> Here the Perſon ſpoken of, is ſaid to be <hi>God</hi> abſolutely; the Church of <hi>God.</hi> And this <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>blood</hi> of his own; the <hi>blood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, being the <hi>blood</hi> of him that was <hi>God,</hi> though not the <hi>blood</hi> of him <hi>as God;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and a Spirit hath <hi>no blood to ſhed:</hi> But it was <hi>Jeſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth, whom the Jews <hi>Crucified,</hi> Acts 4. 10. it is <hi>his Blood</hi> that cleanſeth us from <hi>all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1. 7. And this being conſidered, it undeniably teſtifies to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of his <hi>Perſon</hi> as <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That in <hi>John</hi> 3. 13. <hi>And no man hath aſcended up into Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of man which is in Heaven.</hi> And that in <hi>John</hi> 17. 5. <hi>And now, O Father, glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf, with the glory which I had with thee before the World was.</hi> Now theſe things cannot be applied to the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> taken <hi>Abſtractive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> for <hi>that</hi> had no <hi>Being,</hi> and ſo could have no <hi>Glory</hi> with the Father <hi>before</hi> the World was; neither did he, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> come down from Heaven, nor could he be <hi>in</hi> Heaven and <hi>on</hi> Earth with his <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> at <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> time: And yet as he was both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>one Perſon,</hi> by the Figure <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche,</hi> all this is <hi>truly</hi> ſpoken of him. But why the Quakers ſhould pretend to relieve themſelves <hi>by this Figure,</hi> and ſay, <hi>That the Body is ſometimes called Chriſt,</hi> unleſs they did <hi>own</hi> the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> to be a <hi>part</hi> of Chriſt, I cannot underſtand; becauſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſignifies a <hi>part</hi> of <hi>that whole</hi> of which it is <hi>predicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall prove, <hi>That that very Perſon who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>is alſo called Chriſt.</hi> Joh. 1. 41.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35672:45"/>
               <hi>We have found the Meſſias, which is being interpreted, the Chriſt.</hi> John 4. 25, 26. <hi>The woman ſaith unto him, I know that Meſſias cometh, which is called Chriſt, when he is come, he will tell us all things. Jeſus ſaith unto her, I that ſpeak unto thee am HE. And many moe believed, becauſe of his own word; and ſaid unto the woman, Now we believe, not becauſe of thy ſaying, for we have heard him our ſelves: And know, that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World,</hi> verſ. 41, 42. And this doth not only prove him <hi>to be the Chriſt,</hi> but ſuch a <hi>Perſon</hi> that the People <hi>ſaw</hi> with <hi>their eyes,</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> with <hi>their ears;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Quakers have the confidence to ſay, <hi>Chriſt was never ſeen with Carnal eyes, nor heard with Carnal ears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>name Chriſt</hi> doth <hi>properly</hi> and <hi>really</hi> belong to <hi>him,</hi> is evident.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe he hath <hi>that Name</hi> given him in the holy Scriptures: And the Quakers ſay, <hi>They are a true Declaration of the mind of God;</hi> and therefore he muſt be what the Scripture calls him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe he was <hi>Anointed</hi> with the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> ſo as never any was but he; <hi>for God gave not the Spirit by meaſure unto him,</hi> John 3. 34. and therefore he is <hi>properly and really</hi> the <hi>only</hi> Chriſt and <hi>Saviour</hi> of the World: <hi>Neither is there Salvation in any other; for there is none other Name under Heaven given among men whereby we muſt be ſaved, but by the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>whom the Jews crucified,</hi> Acts 4. 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this point in the words of the Learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> as it is by him applied to that Sacred Perſon before defined: His words are theſe, <hi>Meſſias doth ſolely and ſingularly betoken Chriſt, as it is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted,</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35672:46"/>
John 1. 41. and 4. 25. <hi>For though the word</hi> Maſhiach <hi>in Hebrew, in the Scripture, ſignifieth any Anointed one whatſoever; yet in this Greek form, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, it never ſignifieth but only Chriſt: Nor is the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word uſed in Hebrew Authors, but in the ſame ſenſe; and ſo it is uſed infinitely among them: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſet ſingle, without any other addition, and very often with this addition, Melech Hamaſhiach, the King Meſſias. In this propriety the word is uſed,</hi> Dan. 9. 25, 26. Pſal. 2. 2. <hi>and ſo it was confeſſed by the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Jews.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lightfoots</hi> 2<hi>d Part of his Harmony,</hi> Critica Sacra, <hi>p.</hi> 136.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing Chriſt is thus <hi>exalted</hi> at the Fathers Right-hand, to be a <hi>Prince</hi> and a <hi>Saviour,</hi> to give us <hi>Grace here</hi> to enable us to do his will, and <hi>Glory hereafter</hi> far ſurpaſſing all our Obedience: let us therefore believe in him for the pardon of our ſins, <hi>as he is a Prieſt;</hi> receive his Doctrine, <hi>as he is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet;</hi> and ſubmit to his Laws, <hi>as he is a King:</hi> For whoſoever ſhall be found <hi>ſo doing,</hi> and continue therein <hi>faithful unto death,</hi> they ſhall certainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> which God hath promiſed to them that love him. I ſhall conclude in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:35672:46"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Quakeriſm is Popery Revived: OR, Some of their</hi> Old Opinions <hi>put into a</hi> New Dreſs, <hi>and</hi> Aſſerted <hi>by the</hi> Quakers <hi>to be</hi> New Diſcoveries <hi>of the</hi> Light within them.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere are two</hi> General Principles <hi>muſt be received by</hi> every one <hi>that will be either a</hi> Quaker <hi>or</hi> Papiſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Scriptures of the Old and New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not the Rule of Faith and Practice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there is ſome other Rule of Faith which is Infallible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To prove this I ſhall quote</hi> their own ſayings, <hi>that you may know I do</hi> not wrong them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Quaker ſaith thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> in <hi>Reaſ. ag. Rail.</hi> p. 48. We deny the Scriptures to be the Rule of Faith and Practice, in honor to that Divine Light that was the Author of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edw. Burrough's Works,</hi> p. 62. He that perſwades people to let the Scripture be the Rule of Faith and Practice, would keep people in darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geo. Whitehead, Dip. pl.</hi> p. 13. It's Idolatry to call the Bible the means of our knowing God. <hi>And in his Book, entituled,</hi> Chriſt Aſcended, <hi>p.</hi> 11. You are walking by your fancies and imaginations, who ſet the Scriptures in the place of Chriſt, as your only abſolute Rule and Ground of your Faith and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. W.</hi> in <hi>Enthuſiaſm above Atheiſm,</hi> p. 20. <hi>ſaith,</hi> As for <hi>W. Penn's</hi> ſaying, That our Belief concerning the Scriptures, is that inward Teſtimony that we have received from the Holy Light within us, to the truth of thoſe ſayings: <hi>He concludes thus,</hi> Wherefore the Scriptures are ſo far from being the great Rule of Faith and Practice, that the Light of Chriſt within, is both our Warrant and Rule for Faith in, and Obedience to them: <hi>And in</hi> p. 27. <hi>he blames his Antagoniſt for ſaying,</hi> The Doctrine contained in the Scriptures, is the Rule of Faith and Practice; <hi>telling him,</hi> He ſhould rather have ſaid, A Rule ſubordinate to the great Rule of Faith and Practice; to wit,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35672:47"/>
That Divine Light. <hi>And yet ſaith,</hi> p. 49. But if he pretend the Spirit to be his Rule, then the Scriptures are not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having heard what the</hi> Chief Men <hi>in the</hi> Quakers Miniſtry <hi>have ſaid, be pleaſed to hear what ſome</hi> eminent Popiſh Prieſts <hi>have ſaid, and you will ſee that this is</hi> no new Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Papiſt ſaith thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eckius, Luthers <hi>Antagoniſt, in his Book of Faith and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication:</hi> The end that moved the Evangeliſts to write, was not becauſe they would have their Writings to rule over Religion and Faith, but rather that they ſhould be ſubject unto it.</p>
            <p>Coſter <hi>ſaith the ſame in his</hi> Enchiridion of Controverſies. <hi>And in</hi> Chap. 71. The Scriptures are as a Noſe of Wax, that ſuffers it ſelf to be turned this way, and that way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turrianus,</hi> p. 250. If Chriſt had left no other Rule of our Faith than the Scriptures, we ſhould have had nothing elſe but a Delphian Sword.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de verbo Dei non Scripto, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ſaith,</hi> The way to keep men ſound and undeceived about Religion, is to forbid to the Laity, or worldly men, the reading of the holy Scripture, as being the occaſion of many Hereſies. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. For although the Scriptures is God's Word, nevertheleſs it can have no Authority without the Churches Approbation, being an imperfect, broken, and lame Rule; for there is not comprehended in it all things that are neceſſary for God's Honour and our Salvation, but what is wanting, muſt be ſupplied by unwritten Tradition. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. The proper and principal end of the Scripture was not, that it ſhould be a Rule of Faith, but a profitable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to make men entertain the Doctrine of Preaching.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is ſome other Rule of Faith which <hi>(they both ſay)</hi> is Infallible.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Quaker ſaith,</hi> It's the Light in the Body (immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Inſpiration, or Enthuſiaſm by the Light within them) which is the Infallible Rule.</p>
            <p>George Keith <hi>ſaith,</hi> That <hi>Will. Penn</hi> hath immediate Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as the primary Rule of his Faith and Practice. <hi>See the Quakers own Account of the</hi> Wheeler-ſtreet-Meeting, <hi>p.</hi> 56, 57. <hi>And in anſwer to Mr.</hi> Ives<hi>'s Demand,</hi> To give one evidence that they had Divine Inſpiration for the Rule of their Faith and Practice, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> p. 62. It is ſufficient that we have the witneſs in our ſelves. <hi>Page</hi> 65. We profeſs and experience Immediate and Divine Revelation, as the Ground of our Faith and Teſtimony. <hi>And in his</hi> Looking-Glaſs for Proteſtants, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> And this is our Faith in all theſe particulars,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35672:47"/>
who witneſs unto the Immediate Teachings of God by his Spirit in our hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geo. Whitehead,</hi> Enthuſ. above Atheiſ. <hi>ſaith,</hi> p. 19. But En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm taken ſimply, as a Divine Inſpiration, or breathing into by a Deity, we do aſſert and contend for in the beſt Acceptation. <hi>I never thought the Quakers would have</hi> owned themſelves <hi>to be</hi> Enthuſiaſts <hi>in</hi> Print: <hi>But what may they not come to</hi> in time? <hi>Page</hi> 22, 23. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> We do therefore aſſert the ſufficiency of this Divine Illumination, as being of it ſelf able to ſhew and reveal to us, what we ought to believe and do in all things. <hi>And</hi> p. 24. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> By their Preaching and Writing they proclaim the ſufficiency thereof. <hi>And</hi> p. 52. <hi>to ſhew that they are</hi> free <hi>from</hi> Error <hi>and</hi> Incongruity, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> It is true, that we affirm the light of Chriſt within to be an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Rule, teaching men that follow it, what they ought to know, believe, and do. <hi>And in the ſame page, he ſaith,</hi> That he, <hi>viz. his Antagoniſt,</hi> falſly ſuppoſeth a defect in the Light, and in our Miniſtry directing thereto. <hi>Then they muſt be both of them</hi> ſufficient <hi>and</hi> infallible, <hi>if there be</hi> no defect <hi>in</hi> either.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to proceed: In</hi> p 69. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> The Apoſtles Doctrine contains Rules, but the Light within that gave it forth, was the Rule, the chief or higheſt Rule, for Guidance and Power, and that wherein was the Power of Rule and Government to all true Chriſtians. <hi>And in</hi> p. 58. <hi>he is diſpleaſed much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Antagoniſt</hi> doth not believe, that their Light is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to direct men to believe in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>But is it not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly inſufficient? for that the Quakers who pretend to be guided by that Light,</hi> do not believe in him, <hi>as I have made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. Now when</hi> G. W. <hi>hath thus aſſerted the</hi> ſufficiency <hi>and</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility <hi>of the</hi> Light; <hi>at the cloſe of his Introduction,</hi> p. 16. <hi>Dictator-like, he comes forth like a</hi> Pope <hi>and</hi> General Council, <hi>with a</hi> moſt <hi>dreadful Sentence againſt</hi> all <hi>that will not believe him in theſe words:</hi> To deny the true God, who is Light, is Atheiſm; But to deny his immediate Light in man, is to deny the true God. <hi>Surely this is a</hi> higher piece <hi>of</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs <hi>than Mr.</hi> Ives <hi>can be</hi> ſuppoſed <hi>to be</hi> guilty of, <hi>in ſaying,</hi> The Quakers are no Chriſtians. <hi>I could have alledged</hi> many more Teſtimonies, <hi>but</hi> theſe are ſufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to prove that this is</hi> no new Doctrine, <hi>let us hear what the</hi> Popiſh Prieſts <hi>ſay to</hi> this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Papiſt ſaith,</hi> It is that Body called the Church (or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation) which is the Infallible Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Book, entituled.</hi> A Manual of Contr. <hi>written by a Pomiſh</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:35672:48"/>
               <hi>Prieſt, lays this down for an</hi> Article of Faith, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is Infallible in all her Propoſitions and Definitions of Faith, and is ſo to be received under pain of Damnation: <hi>And this is known to be their</hi> profeſſed Principle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellar. de verb. Dei Interp.</hi> Thoſe that ſpeak againſt the Popes Decrees and Humane Inſtitutions, are falſe Teachers: For the Pope hath Power and Authority to judg in all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies in Doctrine, and to give forth the right meaning of the holy Scripture; and no man may appeal from his judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charon's</hi> Third Truth, chap. 2. <hi>having ſaid,</hi> That the Church and <hi>the</hi> Scripture are Judges together: <hi>He adds,</hi> But the Church is primarily, and principally, and with great prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence; <hi>and a little after,</hi> The Scripture is not, nor cannot be the laſt Rule, and Soveveign Judg of Doctrine And <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. Faith that is neceſſary to Salvation, comes from the Churches ſpeaking, and not from the Reading of the Scripture: Without knowing of which, after a ſort, yea, and without believing or obeying it expreſly, a thouſand millions are ſaved. And to be ſhort, a man may be a Chriſtian, and a good Chriſtian, and be ſaved, without the Scripture; but not without the Church: for the Scripture hath no Authority, Weight, or Power over us, but only ſo much as the Church doth allow and aſſign unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Boook, entituled,</hi> Reaſon againſt Railery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 7. <hi>are theſe words,</hi> It may be asked when one pitches upon a determinate ſenſe of any place beyond what the Letter inforces, by what light he guides himſelf in that Determination? <hi>And then anſwers,</hi> That that Light, whatever it is, and not the Letter, is indeed the formal Revealer, or Rule of Faith. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the next Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph,</hi> The Letter-Rule ſecluded, I advanced <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to prove, That Tradition, or that Body called the Church, taken as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering her thoughts, by a conſtant Tenor of living Voyce and Practice, viſible to the whole World, is the abſolute certain way of conveying down the Doctrine taught at firſt.</p>
            <p>In <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Stillingfleeton,</hi> &amp;c. Part 2. p. 19. <hi>it's ſaid,</hi> That Divine Revelation is firmer and more Authentick, than either Scripture, or our ſeeing; <hi>and again,</hi> It is the ſole ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unextinguiſhable general Light, ſet up for the aſſured Guidance of all men. <hi>And</hi> p. 27. They are certain, and know themſelves certain, and declare ſo much before the face of the Sun, and all the eyes of Heaven, by their ſtability, fixedneſs, and immovability in Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In another Popiſh Book, entituled,</hi> A Rational Compendious way, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 31. The Roman Catholick Religion doth not teach
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35672:48"/>
any thing as an Article of Faith, which is either an Error, or a Corruption. And <hi>p.</hi> 30. The Roman Church is infallible and perpetual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now from what hath been ſaid, we may draw this Concluſion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That if</hi> W. L. <hi>ſay true,</hi> That he is no Chriſtian who denies the Divinity of Chriſt: <hi>If he means in the</hi> common ſenſe, <hi>viz. as he is the</hi> Second Perſon <hi>in the</hi> Divine Eſſence; <hi>then the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are no Chriſtians, <hi>for in</hi> that ſenſe <hi>they deny the Divinity of Chriſt, in denying the Trinity of Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That they do</hi> really deny <hi>the Humane Nature</hi> to be a part of Chriſt; <hi>and that</hi> Sacred Perſon <hi>whom</hi> God <hi>hath</hi> Anointed <hi>with the</hi> Holy Spirit, <hi>who is both</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Man, The man Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>to be</hi> the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World: <hi>And ſo fulfil</hi> that <hi>Prophecy,</hi> Even denying the Lord that bought them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>From hence it follows,</hi> That the Quakers have no Chriſt at all, <hi>but one of</hi> their own ſetting up and adoring: <hi>For the</hi> name Chriſt <hi>cannot be</hi> properly applied <hi>to the</hi> Divine Nature, <hi>taken</hi> Abſtractively; <hi>as I have</hi> fully proved. <hi>And</hi> they confeſs <hi>they</hi> own no other Chriſt, <hi>but</hi> the Light within them; <hi>which</hi> they ſay <hi>is</hi> only God, <hi>though</hi> in truth, <hi>it is but</hi> a created Light, <hi>and</hi> they Idolaters, <hi>in worſhipping</hi> a Creature, <hi>inſtead of the</hi> Creator.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If he be no Chriſtian that hath no Rule for his Faith and Practice, then the Quakers are no Chriſtians; for they have no Rule for their Faith and Practice. <hi>For,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They confeſs the holy Scriptures are not their Rule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's apparent <hi>(notwithſtanding their high pretences)</hi> they have not Divine and Immediate Revelation for their Rule; <hi>for they cannot demonſtrate it</hi> by Scripture, right Reaſon, nor any other way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus I have uſed</hi> my endeavour, <hi>according to the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 25, 26. In meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance, to the acknowledging of the Truth. And that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who are taken captive by him at his will. <hi>The Lord open the eyes of their underſtanding, and</hi> bleſs <hi>this Treatiſe to all thoſe good</hi> ends <hi>and</hi> purpoſes <hi>for which it is</hi> intended: To whom be glory in the Churches by Chriſt Jeſus throughout all Ages, World without end. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Ruſſel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:35672:49"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Here followeth a Letter from the Baptized-Congregation in</hi> Reading, <hi>concerning</hi> William Luddington.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Brother</hi> Ives,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours, and adviſed with the Brethren, about <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>the Anſwer;</hi> which is, <hi>That we do not own</hi> William Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington <hi>in any ſuch Relation as Communion with us, neither do we know any Principle of Religion that he is ſtedfaſt to.</hi> But about ten or twelve years ſince he was here in Priſon, and <hi>blamed</hi> much, <hi>for refuſing to give God thanks for any of his Mercies, or to joyn with them that did,</hi> with many other <hi>ſtrange Humours,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Maſon</hi> can tell you) not ſuiting with <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion:</hi> But was looked upon by all <hi>to be a Quaker,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>a ſuppoſed Behmeniſt;</hi> which <hi>uncertain Fictions</hi> beſt ſuited <hi>his wandring Fancy.</hi> Sometimes he is for <hi>univerſal Communion</hi> with <hi>all ſorts</hi> (as he calls it:) And ſometimes ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>Forms,</hi> and ſays, <hi>He never preached for Baptiſm, nor never would:</hi> For that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>To the end of the World,</hi> he ſays, <hi>was to the end of that Age.</hi> And he had wrote a Book two years ſince <hi>to that purpoſe,</hi> and going to print it: But Mr. <hi>Maynard</hi> perſwaded him to the contrary. So that for this <hi>Ten years paſt,</hi> we have been ſo far from <hi>any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> that we have had little <hi>Religious Converſe;</hi> neither did we ever find he deſired <hi>any</hi> with <hi>us.</hi> And as for <hi>his writing</hi> on the <hi>behalf</hi> of <hi>the Quakers,</hi> he hath done <hi>them</hi> ſo little ſervice <hi>here,</hi> that he hath only <hi>diſcovered</hi> his <hi>folly,</hi> and made <hi>his beſt Friends aſhamed of him;</hi> and many <hi>others</hi> ſay, <hi>they</hi> were <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in him.</hi> So that we may ſay, He hath here met with the juſt reward of his <hi>folly,</hi> and is <hi>diſcerned</hi> by all <hi>ſober,</hi> rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Chriſtians; and left only to be ſupported (if by any) <hi>by ſuch giddy Brains,</hi> that will lay hold on any rotten Poſt, to ſupport <hi>a Tottering Building.</hi> But at laſt <hi>yours</hi> came, and was <hi>ſo acceptable,</hi> that <hi>your Enemies</hi> ſay, <hi>you have gained great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by your diſcrcet managing that Buſineſs:</hi> And you have <hi>morae raiſed</hi> the <hi>hearts of all</hi> your (and the Lord's) truly loving Friends <hi>towards you.</hi> And as it is common for men that want <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> or good <hi>Argument</hi> for what they would have, to ſupply it with <hi>Railing,</hi> and <hi>abundance of words, ſo your</hi> Adverſaries have done. But God hath furniſhed you better, as appears by your managing this buſineſs. To whoſe guidance we leave you, with our prayers, that you may be kept to the end: And reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Brethren in Chriſt.</hi> Signed by conſent, By <hi>Daniel Roberts.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>Reading, <date>
                     <hi>this 6th of</hi> Decemb. 1674.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
